我相信美国
I believe in America.
美国使我发了财
America has made my fortune
而我以美国方式教养我的女儿
and I raised my daughter in the American fashion.
我给她自由
I give her freedom, but
但也告诉她永远不要有辱家门
I taught her never to dishonor her family.
她交了位男友  但不是意大利人
She found a boyfriend. Not an Italian.
她跟他去看电影  深夜才回家
She went to the movies with him. She stayed out late.
我并没有责骂她
I didn't protest.
两个月前他与另一个男孩
Two months ago, he took her for a drive
带她去兜风
with another boyfriend.
他们强灌她喝威士忌
They made her drink whiskey
然后他们想要占她便宜
and then they tried to take advantage of her.
她抵抗  她保住了名节
She resisted. She kept her honor.
于是他们像对动物般的毒打她
So they beat her like an animal.
当我到医院时
When I went to the hospital,
她的鼻梁断了
her nose was broken
她的下巴被打碎了
her jaw was shattered
必须用钢丝绑着才不会掉下来
held together by wire.
她痛得不能哭
She couldn't even weep because of the pain.
但我却哭了  我为什么哭呢？
But I wept. Why did I weep?
我视她如珠如宝
She was the light of my life.
长得很美丽
Beautiful girl.
现在她再也美丽不起来
Now she will never be beautiful again.
不好意思
Sorry.
我像个守法的美国人一样
I went to the police
我去报警
like a good American.
那两个男孩受到了审判
These two boys were brought to trial.
法官判他们有期徒刑三年但缓期执行
Ajudge sentence them to three years in prison and suspend their sentence.
缓期执行
Suspended sentence.
他们当天就没事了
They went free that very day.
我像个傻瓜似的站在法庭中
I stood in the courtroom like a fool.
而那两个混蛋竟朝着我笑
And those two bastard, they smiled at me.
于是我对我太太说
Then I said to my wife,
为求公道我们必须去找柯里昂阁下
''For justice we must go to Don Corleone.''
你去报警前为何不先来找我？
Why did you go to the police? Why didn't you come to me first?
你要我怎么样？
What do you want of me?
你尽管吩咐但求你一定要帮我这个忙
Tell me anything, but do what I beg you to do.
帮你什么忙？
What is that?
那个我办不到
That I cannot do.
你要什么我都会给你
I'll give you anything you ask.
我们相识多年
We've known each other many years, but this is
这是你第一次来找我帮忙
the first time you ever came to me for counsel or for help.
我记不起你上次是何时请我到你家去喝咖啡了
I can't remember the last time that you invited me to your house for a cup of coffee
何况我太太还是你独生女的教母
even though my wife is godmother to your only child.
我坦白说吧
But let's be frank.
你从来就不想要我的友谊
You never wanted my friendship
而且你怕欠我人情
and you were afraid to be in my debt.
我不想卷入是非
I didn't want to get into trouble.
我了解
I understand.
你在美国发了财
You found paradise in America.
生意做的很好  生活过的很好
You had a good trade, made a good living.
有警察和法律保护你
Police protected you, and there were courts of law.
你不需要我这种朋友
So you didn't need a friend like me.
但是...
But...
现在你来找我说
now you come to me and you say
柯里昂阁下  请帮我主持公道
''Don Corleone, give me justice.''
但你对我一点尊重也没有
But you don't ask with respect.
你并不把我当朋友
You don't offer friendship.
你甚至不愿意喊我教父
You don't even think to call me ''Godfather.''
你在我女儿结婚当天来我家
Instead, you come into my house on the day my daughter is to be married
用钱收买我为你杀人
and you ask me to do murder for money.
我只是要求你主持公道
I ask you for justice.
那不是公道  你女儿还活着
That is not justice. Your daughter is still alive.
那么让他们像她一样受折磨
They must suffer then as she suffers.
我应该付你多少钱？
How much shall I pay you?
包纳萨拉
Bonasera.
到底我做了什么
What have I ever done
让你这么的不尊重我
to make you treat me so disrespectfully?
如果你以朋友身份来找我
If you'd come to me in friendship
那么伤害你女儿的杂碎就会受到折磨
then the scum that ruined your daughter would be suffering this very day.
你这种诚实人的敌人
And if, by chance an honest man like yourself
也就是我的敌人
should make enemies then they would become my enemies.
那么  他们就会怕你
And then they would fear you.
当我的朋友？
Be my friend?
教父
Godfather.
很好
Good.
他日我或需要你的帮忙
Someday, and that day may never come
也可能不会有那么一天
I'll call upon you to do a service for me.
但在那一天到来之前
But until that day
收下这份公道做为小女结婚之礼
accept this justice as a gift on my daughter's wedding day.
- 谢谢  教父  - 别客气
- Grazie, Godfather. - Prego.
这件事交给... 克里曼沙
Give this to Clemenza.
我要用可靠的人头脑清醒的人
I want reliable people people that aren't going to be carried away.
我们不是谋杀犯  下手别太重
I mean, we're not murderers in spite of what this undertaker says.
- 麦克在哪？  - 别担心  他一会就来
- Where's Michael? - What? Don't worry. It's early. He'll be here.
没有麦克我不照相
We're not taking the picture without Michael.
待会再拍
Taking it later.
- 什么事？  - 麦克的事
- What's the matter, Sonny? - It's Michael.
你好  巴西尼阁下
Don Barzini.
你认得我儿子吧？
保利  让我喝点酒
Hey, Paulie! Let me have some wine.
保利  再来点酒
Paulie! More wine.
- 你看起来棒极了  - 你是裁判还是什么？
- You look terrific on the floor. - Are you a dance judge or something?
闪开吧  到附近晃晃做你的工作
Go take a walk around the neighborhood. Do your job.
仙杜拉  帮个忙别让孩子乱跑  好吗？
Sandra, come on. Do me a favor. Watch the kids. Don't let them run wild.
你看好你自己  好吗？
- You watch yourself, all right?
两三万元小钞  全是现金
Twenty or thirty grand. In small bills, cash.
全在那个小丝袋里
In that little silk purse.
如果这是我的婚礼我就发财了
If this were somebody else's wedding... Sfortunato!
保利  接住吧
Hey, Paulie! I got two gobbagool gabagol and a prosciutto.
你这个笨蛋
Stupid jerk!
怎么回事？
Hey, what's the matter?
- 我得回去工作了  - 汤姆
- Have to go back to work. - Tom.
这是婚礼的一部分
It's part of the wedding.
没有西西里人在女儿结婚那天能拒绝任何的请求
No Sicilian can refuse any request on his daughter's wedding day.
柯里昂阁下能受邀到贵府深感荣幸
Don Corleone, I am honored and grateful that you have invited me to your home-
你们在干什么？滚
Get outta here.
这是私人宴会  快滚
This is a private party. Go on.
这算什么？是我妹妹的婚礼
What is it? Hey, my sister's wedding.
该死的联邦密探什么都不尊重
Goddamn FBI don't respect nothing!
过来 过来
Hey, come here, come here. Come here!There.
但最后他获假释去为美国作战
But towards the end he was paroled to help with the American war effort.
过去六个月他在我的糕饼店做事
For the last six months, he's been working at my pastry shop.
纳色利  我的朋友我能为你做什么？
Nazorine, my friend, what can I do for you?
现在战争结束了
Now that the war is over
这男孩  安索他们要把他遣返意大利
this boy, Enzo, they want to repatriate him back to Italy.
教父  我有个女儿她和安索...
Godfather, I have a daughter. See, she and Enzo-
你要安索留在这个国家和你女儿成亲
You want Enzo to stay in this country and you want your daughter to be married.
你什么都了解  谢谢
You understand everything.
哈金先生  谢谢
Mr. Hagen. Thank you.
待会看看我为你女儿做的结婚蛋糕
And wait till you see the beautiful wedding cake I made for your daughter.
这么高... 还有一对新人和天使
Like this, The bride, the groom and the angel...
这件事我该交给谁去办？
- Who should I give this job to?
别给我们这个选区
- Not to our paisan.
给别地区的犹太籍众议员
Give it to a Jew congressman in another district.
名单上还有谁？
Who else is on the list?
你好  麦克
Hey, Michael. How are you? Hello.
路卡布拉西不在名单上  但他想要见你
He's not on the list, but Luca Brasi wants to see you.
这个... 有这个必要吗？
Is this... is this necessary?
他没料到会受邀参加婚礼所以要向你致谢
He didn't expect to be invited to the wedding so he wanted to thank you.
好吧
All right.
柯里昂阁下  在令嫒婚礼这天
Don Corleone, I am honored and grateful that you have invited me to your home
能受邀到贵府深感荣幸
on the wedding day of your daughter.
希望他们早生贵子
And may their first child be a masculine child.
麦克
Michael?
那边的那个人在自言自语
That man over there is talking to himself.
看到那边那个吓人的家伙了吗？
See that scary guy over there?
- 他很叫人害怕  - 他是谁？叫什么名字？
He's a very scary guy.Who is he? What's his name?
他叫做路卡布拉西  有时候替家父办事
His name is Luca Brasi and he helps my father out sometimes.
麦克  等一下  他过来了
Wait a minute. He's coming over here.
麦克
Michael!
汤姆
Tom!
你气色好极了
You look terrific!
家兄汤姆·哈金  这是凯亚·当斯
My brother Tom Hagen. This is Kay Adams.
- 你好  - 你好
How do you do? Nice to meet you.
你父亲要见你
Your father's been asking for you.
- 幸会  - 幸会
- Very nice to meet you. - Nice to meet you.
若他是你哥哥  为何不同姓？
If he's your brother, why does he have a different name?
小时候在街上发现汤姆无家可归
When my brother Sonny was a kid he found Tom Hagen in the street, and he had no home.
所以家父收养了他
So my father took him in
从此他就和我们住在一起了
and he's been with us ever since.
他是个好律师
He's a good lawyer.
不是西西里人  但我想他会当军师
Not a Sicilian, but I think he's gonna be consigliere.
- 那是什么？  - 那是...
- What's that? - That's
像是个顾问  在家族中的地位非常重要
like a counselor, an advisor. Very important to the family.
你的扁形通心面还好吧？
You like your lasagna?
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone
在令嫒的婚礼受到邀请
I am honored and grateful that you have invited me
深感荣幸与感激
to your daughter's wedding
在令嫒结婚的当天
on the day of your daughter's wedding.
我希望他们能早生贵子
And I hope that their first child be a masculine child.
这是我一点小小的心意
I pledge my ever-ending loyalty.
- 祝福他们俩白头偕老  - 谢谢你  路卡
For your daughter's bridal purse. Thank you, Luca,
我最珍贵的朋友
my most valued friend.
柯里昂阁下  我晓得你忙我先告退了
Don Corleone, I'm gonna leave you now because I know you are busy.
谢谢
Thank you.
柯里昂夫人
Signora Corleone!
不...
No.
科利参议员对不能亲自来致歉
Senator Cauly apologized for not coming personally
他说你会谅解的
but said you'd understand.
还有一些法官也一样他们都送了礼物
Also some of the judges.They've all sent gifts.
敬你
外面是怎么回事？
What is that outside?
强尼
Johnny!
我爱你
I love you. Hey, Johnny, look over here!
他大老远由加州赶来参加婚礼
He came all the way from California to come to the wedding.
我告诉过你他会来的
I told you he was going to come.
已经两年了  他也许又有麻烦
- It's been two years. - He's probably in trouble again.
他是个好教子
He's a good godson.
强尼...  唱首歌
Johnny, Johnny! Sing a song!
麦克你从未告诉我你认得强尼·方亭
Michael, you never told me you knew Johnny Fontane.
- 你想见他吗  - 当然
- Sure. You wanna meet him? - Huh? Oh, well, sure.
- 家父帮他建立他的事业  - 真的
- My father helped him with his career. - He did?
怎么做的？
How?
- 我们先听这首唱  - 不  麦克
- Let's listen to the song. - No.
拜托  麦克  告诉我
Please, Michael. Tell me.
强尼刚出道时和一个乐队领班签了合约
When Johnny was first starting out.. he was signed to this personal service contract with a big bandleader.
当他走红后  想要解除合约
And as his career got better and better he wanted to get out of it.
强尼是家父的教子
Now, Johnny is my father's godson
于是家父去见乐队负责人
and my father went to see this bandleader
而且出一万元要他与强尼解约
and he offered him $ 10,000 to let Johnny go.
他说不行
But the bandleader said no.
第二天家父再去见他  只是这次带着路卡布拉西
So the next day my father went to see him only this time with Luca Brasi.
一个小时之内
And within an hour,
他签了解约书只收了一千元的支票
he signed a release for a certified check of $ 1,000.
他是怎么办到的？
How'd he do that?
家父提了个他不能拒绝的条件
My father made him an offer he couldn't refuse.
那是什么？
What was that?
路卡布拉西用枪顶着他的头
Luca Brasi held a gun to his head
他要是不签字脑袋就会开花
and my father assured him that either his brains or his signature would be on the contract.
这是真实的故事
That's a true story.
凯  那是我的家庭  不是我
That's my family, Kay. It's not me.
我会处理的
I'll take care of it.
汤姆
Tom...
叫山提诺来我的办公室
I want you to find Santino. Tell him to come to the office.
你好吗？弗雷多
How are you, Fredo?
- 家兄弗雷多  - 这位是凯亚当斯
Fredo, my brother Fredo. This is Kay Adams.
- 你好  - 你好吗？
- Hi. - How ya doin'?
- 这是舍弟麦克  - 玩的愉快吗？
- This is my brother Mike. - Are you having a good time?
这是你的朋友？
Yeah. This is your friend, huh?
我不知道该怎么办
I don't know what to do.
我的嗓子很虚弱  很虚弱
My voice is weak. It's weak.
总之我若能得到那部戏的角色
Anyway, if I had this part in the picture you know
我会再次走红的
it puts me right back up on top again.
但是电影公司的老板不让我演
But this this man out there, he won't give it to me. The head of the studio.
- 他叫什么名字？  - 华尔斯
- What's his name? - Woltz.
他不肯让我演而且还说门都没有
He won't give it to me and he says there's no chance, no chance.
山尼？
Sonny?
山尼？你在里面吗？
Sonny, you in there?
什么事？
What?
老头子要见你
The old man wants to see you.
好  马上去
Yeah, one minute.
山尼
Sonny
一个月以前
A month ago,
他买下这本畅销书的电影版权
he bought the movie rights to this book.A best-seller.
男主角就像是我的写照
And the main character is a guy just like me.
我根本不需要演只要当我自己即可
Why, I wouldn't even have to act.Just be myself.
但... 教父  我不知该怎么办？
Oh, Godfather, I don't know what to do. I don't know what to do.
你要表现得像个男人
You are gonna to act like a man!
你是怎么回事？
What's the matter with you?
这就是你在好莱坞学到的？
Is this how you turned out a Hollywood finocchio
哭的像个女人？
that cries like a woman?
该怎么办？怎么办？
''What can I do? What can I do?''
算什么鬼话？
What is that nonsense?
岂有此理
Ridiculous!
- 你有花时间与家人共聚吗？  - 我当然有
- You spend time with your family? - Sure I do.
很好
Good.
因为不抽空陪家人的男人不是真正的男人
Because the man who doesn't spend time with his family can never be a real man.
过来这
Come here.
你看来糟透了  我要你多吃点
You look terrible. I want you to eat.
好好休息
I want you to rest well, and
从现在起一个月内好莱坞大亨会让你愿望成真
a month from now this Hollywood big shot's gonna give you what you want.
太迟了他们一周内就要开拍了
Too late. They start shooting in a week.
我会给他一个他无法拒绝的提议
I'm gonna make him an offer he can't refuse.
现在你到外面去好好的玩
Now just go outside, enjoy yourself and forget about all this nonsense.
- 其他的交给我来办  - 好的
- Listen. I want you to leave it all to me. - All right.
我女儿女婿何时离开？
What time does my daughter leave with the bridegroom?
切完蛋糕后的几分钟
In a few minutes, right after they cut the cake.
你的新女婿要给重要职务吗？
Now, your new son-in-law, we give him something important.
永远不要
Never.
让他们过好日子但别让他插手家族中的事
Give him a living but never discuss the family business with him.
还有什么事？
What else?
威尔斯索拉索来过电话
Virgil Sollozzo called.
下周我们必须安排跟他见面
We have to give him a day sometime next week.
等你从加州回来我们再讨论
We'll discuss him when you come back from California.
我何时要去加州了？
When am I going to California?
我要你今晚去
I want you to go tonight.
我要你和这个...
I want you to talk to this
电影大亨谈谈把强尼的事摆平
movie big shot and settle this business for Johnny.
若没有其他事我想去参加我女儿的婚礼了
If there's nothing else, I'd like to go to my daughter's wedding.
卡洛  我们要拍照了
Carlo, we're gonna take the picture.
等一下
Wait a minute.
不  麦克  我不行
No, Michael, not me.
好了  就是这样  别动
Just a little closer.Okay, that's it. Just like that now. Hold it.
好了  开始说吧
All right, start talking.
我是强尼·方亭的朋友派来的
I was sent by a friend of Johnny Fontane.
他的朋友是我的委托人
This friend is my client
若是华尔斯先生能帮他个小忙
and would give his undying friendship to Mr. Woltz
他将会感激不尽
if Mr. Woltz would grant us a small favor.
继续说下去
Woltz is listening.
把你下周开拍的新片男主角让强尼担任
Give Johnny the part in that new war film you're starting next week.
他的朋友会回报我什么好处？
And what favor would your friend grant Mr. Woltz?
你若有工会问题我的委托人能摆平
You're gonna have some union problems.My client could make them disappear.
而你旗下一位抽大麻的大牌
Also, one of your top stars has just moved from
现在吸起海洛因了
marijuana to heroin.
你想要威胁我吗？
- Are you trying to muscle me? - Absolutely not.
绝对没有  我只是...
Absolutely not.
听着你这个油腔滑调的王八蛋
Listen to me, you smooth-talking son of a bitch!
让我对你及你的老板说清楚不管他是何许人
Let me lay it on the line for you and your boss, whoever he is!
强尼·方亭绝对得不到那个角色
Johnny Fontane will never get that movie.
我不在乎有多少意大利的移民来找我麻烦
I don't care how many dago, guinea, wop greaseball goombahs come outta the woodwork.
我是德裔爱尔兰人
I'm German-Irish.
坦白告诉你  德国朋友
Well, let me tell you something, my kraut mick friend.
你大祸临头了  你甚至不会晓得是谁扁你
I'll make so much trouble for you, you won't know what hit you.
华尔斯先生  我是位律师我不是来威胁你
I'm a lawyer. I have not threatened-
我认识纽约的每位大律师你是谁？
I know almost every big lawyer in New York. Who are you?
我的执业情况很特别  只为一位委托人办事
I have a special practice. I handle one client.
你有我的电话号码  我等你电话
Now, you have my number. I'll wait for your call.
告诉你  我很喜欢你的电影
By the way, I admire your pictures very much.
摸清他的底细
Check him out.
真是美极了
- This is really beautiful.
看看这个原本是用来装饰王宫的
- Look at this.Used to decorate the palace of a king.
很漂亮
Oh, yeah. Very nice.
你为何不说你为柯里昂阁下做事
Why didn't you say you worked for Corleone, Tom?
我以为你只是个市井流氓
I thought you were just some cheap, two-bit hustler
是强尼派来勒索我的
Johnny was running in, trying to bluff me.
除非真的必要  否则我不想提起他的名字
I don't like to use his name unless it's really necessary.
- 你的酒还好吗？  - 很好
- How's your drink, Tom? - Fine.
到这边来  让你看看真正漂亮的东西
Come with me. I want to show you something really beautiful.
你的眼光应该不错吧？
You do appreciate beauty, don't you, Tom?
这里  这匹马价值六十万元
There you are. $600,000 on four hooves.
我敢说俄国沙皇也从未在马身上花那么大笔钱
I'll bet Russian czars never paid that kind of dough for a single horse.
达通
Khartoum.
不过我不会用它们来比赛  我要它们当种马
I'm not gonna race him, though. I'm gonna put him out to stud.
- 谢谢  汤尼  - 不必客气
- Thanks, Tony. - You're welcome.
我们去吃点东西吧
- Come on. - Let's get something to eat.
柯里昂是强尼的教父
Mr. Corleone is Johnny's godfather.
对意大利人而言  那是种宗教上神圣的亲密关系
To the Italian people, that's a very religious sacred, close relationship.
我很敬重这点
I respect that.
告诉他除了这件事
Just tell him he should ask me anything else.
我什么都答应
This is one favor I can't give him.
他被拒绝一次后不会再要求第二次
He never asks a second favor when he's been refused the first.
你不了解  强尼·方亭永远别想演那部电影
- Understood? - You don't understand.Johnny Fontane never gets that movie.
他很适合那个角色
That part is perfect for him.
会让他成为巨星
It'll make him a big star.
但我要让他走投无路
I'm gonna run him out of the business.
我告诉你为什么
Let me tell you why.
强尼毁了一位华尔斯国际公司最有前途的女星
Johnny Fontane ruined one of Woltz International's most valuable proteges.
五年来我们不断地训练她
For five years, we had her under training.
歌唱课  表演课  跳舞课
Singing lessons, acting lessons, dancing lessons.
我在她身上投资了无数的金钱
I spent hundreds of thousands of dollars on her.
我要让她成为一位巨星
I was gonna make her a big star.
让我更坦白的告诉你
And let me be even more frank.
让你知道我不是铁石心肠也不是势利眼
Just to show you that I'm not a hard-hearted man that it's not all dollars and cents.
她年轻漂亮  天真无邪
She was beautiful. She was young, she was innocent!
我拥有她就等于拥有全世界
She was the greatest piece of ass I've ever had and I've had 'em all over the world!
然后强尼·方亭出现了
And then Johnny Fontane comes along with his olive oil
带着磁性的嗓音加上意大利的魅力
voice and guinea charm.
把她拐走了
And she runs off.
她跑掉了使我非常难堪
She threw it all away just to make me look ridiculous
而我这种地位的人无法忍受难堪
and a man in my position can't afford to be made to look ridiculous!
你马上给我滚
Now you get the hell outta here!
若是那混球想对我动粗
And if that goombah tries any rough stuff
你告诉他我不是乐队领班
you tell him I ain't no bandleader.
我听过那个故事了
Yeah. I heard that story.
谢谢你的晚餐款待
Thank you for the dinner and a very pleasant evening.
也许你能派车送我去机场
If your car could take me to the airport
柯里昂先生坚持坏消息要立刻回报
Mr. Corleone is a man who insists on hearing bad news immediately.
- 你不会太累吧？汤姆  - 我在飞机上睡过了
- You're not too tired, Tom? - No, I slept on the plane.
我这里有索拉索的资料
I have the Sollozzo notes here.
众人皆知  索拉索是土耳其人
Now Sollozzo is known as ''The Turk.''
他应该善于用刀
He's supposed to be very good with a knife
但只有发生利益冲突时才会使用
but only in matters of business with some sort of reasonable complaint.
他是做毒品生意的
his business is narcotics.
他们在土耳其种罂粟
he has fields in Turkey where they grow the poppy
在西西里有工厂提炼成海洛因
and in Sicily he has the plants to process them into heroin.
他需要现金
Now, he needs cash and
以及在毒品交易时需要警方的保护
he needs protection from the police for which he gives a piece of the action.
我无法查出保护费价钱多少
I couldn't find out how much.
在纽约是塔塔基利亚家族在保护他
The Tattaglia family is behind him here in New York.
他们一定也想分占利益
Now, they have to be in it for something.
山尼·柯里昂
Santino Corleone.
- 他的犯罪前科呢？  - 一次在意大利  一次在这
What about his prison record?Two terms, one in Italy, one here.
他是众所周知的大毒枭
He's known as a top narcotics man.
山提诺  你认为呢？
Santino, what do you think?
白粉可以赚大钱
There's a lot of money in that white powder.
我赞成  毒品比什么都好赚
Tom? I say, yes, there's more money potential in narcotics than anything else we're looking at.
就算我们不加入  别人也会
If we don't get into it, somebody else will.
也许是五大家族之一也许全部都会
Maybe one of the five families, maybe all of them.
他们会用毒品赚到的钱买通警方和政客
With the money they earn they can buy more police and political power.
到时就会赶上我们
Then they come after us.
现在我们掌握了工会及赌场
Now we have the unions, we have the gambling
而他们却掌握未来最好的东西毒品
and they're the best things to have, but narcotics is a thing of the future.
我们若不能分一杯羹
If we don't get a piece of that action
我们可能会失去一切
we risk everything we have.
我不是指现在而是在十年之内
Not now, but ten years from now.
你的答案是什么呢？爸爸
So? What's your answer gonna be, Pop?
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone,
我需要有势力的友人
I need a man who has powerful friends.
我需要一百万元的现金
I need a million dollars in cash.
我需要你手中掌握的政客
I need those politicians that you carry in your pocket, like nickels and dimes.
- 对我家族有什么利益？  - 三成
- What is the interest for my family? - 30 per cent.
第一年你就可进帐三四百万元
In the first year, your end should be 3, 4 million dollars.
然后还会增加
And then it would go up.
塔塔基利亚家族会得到什么好处？
And what is the interest for the Tattaglia family?
我的敬意
My compliments.
我会从我那一份当中分给他们
I'll take care of the Tattaglias outta my share.
我提供财务 政治和法律的保护可以分到三成  这就是你想说的
So, I receive 30% for finance political influence and legal protection.That's what you're telling me
没错
-  That's right.
你为何来找我
Why do you come to me?
我为何值得你这么慷慨？
Why do I deserve this generosity?
若你能考虑投资一百万元现金
If you consider a million dollars in cash just finance,
我就会向你敬礼  柯里昂阁下
ti saluto, Don Corleone.
我肯见你是因为我听说你是个正直的人
I said that I would see you because I heard that you were a serious man
所以我以礼相待
to be treated with respect.
但是我必须拒绝你
But I must say no to you.
我会告诉你原因
And I'll give you my reason.
没错  我是有很多政界的朋友
It's true, I have a lot of friends in politics.
但若他们知道我在搞毒品生意而不再是赌博时
But they wouldn't be friendly very long if they knew my business
他们就不再是我的朋友
was drugs instead of gambling
他们认为赌博只是些无伤大雅的事业
which they regard as a harmless vice.
但毒品是败坏德性的生意
- But drugs is a dirty business.
- 但是柯里昂阁下...   - 对我而言一个人以何为生
- No, Don Corleone - It doesn't make any difference to me
并没有什么差别
what a man does for a living, you understand
但你这种生意... 有一点危险性
but your business is a little dangerous.
若你还是担心安全的问题
If you're worried about security for your million
塔塔基利亚会做保证的
the Tattaglias will guarantee it.
你是说塔塔基利亚家族会保证我们的投资...
You're tellin' me the Tattaglias guarantee our investment-
等一下
Wait a minute.
你看我把孩子都给宠坏了
I have a sentimental weakness for my children and I spoil them, as you can see.
他们说话非常没有分寸
They talk when they should listen.
但总之  索拉索先生
But anyway Signor Sollozzo,
我的决定还是不行
my ''no'' is final
我要恭喜你的生意
and I wish to congratulate you on your new business.
我知道你会很成功... 我祝你好运
I know you'll do very well, and good luck to you
尤其是你的生意不会与我的冲突
especially since your interests don't conflict with mine.
谢谢
Thank you.
山提诺
Santino.
到这来
Come here.
你是怎么回事？
What's the matter with you?
我看你和女孩子胡搞之后脑子退化了
I think your brain is going soft from all that comedy you're playing with that young girl.
别让外人知道你在想什么
Never tell anybody outside the family what you're thinking again.
走吧
Go on.
汤姆  这是什么乱七八糟的？
Tom, what... what is this nonsense?
那是强尼送的  他主演了那部新电影
It's from Johnny. He's starring in that new film.
好了  把它拿走
Well, take it away.
把它放到那去
Take it over there.
还有
And
叫路卡布拉西到这来
tell Luca Brasi to come in.
我对这索拉索有点担心
I'm a little worried about this Sollozzo fellow.
我要你弄清楚他在耍什么把戏
I want you to find out what he's got under his fingernails, you know.
到塔塔基利亚那边去
Go to the Tattaglias and
让他们以为你与我们家族不融洽
make them think that you're not too happy with our family
尽量查
and find out what you can.
我买了东西给令堂
And I got something for your mother and for Sonny
还有给弗雷多的领带  给汤姆的钢笔
and a tie for Freddy and Tom Hagen got the Reynolds pen.
- 你圣诞节想要什么？  - 我只要你
- What do you want for Christmas? - Me? Oh, just you.
醒醒  弗雷多
Andiamo, Fredo.
叫保利备车  我们要走了
Tell Paulie to get the car. We're going.
好的  爸
Okay, Pa.
我来开车  保利今早生病了
I'll have to get it myself. Paulie called in sick this morning.
保利是个好孩子  我不介意自己开车
Paulie's a good kid. I don't mind gettin' the car.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 路卡  我是布诺塔塔基利亚  - 我知道
- Luca,I am Bruno Tattaglia. - I know.
想喝杯威士忌吗？
Scotch?
先暖和一下
Prewar.
我不喝酒
你知道我是谁吗？
You know who I am?
我认识你
Yeah.
你和塔塔基利亚家族谈过了对吧？
You have been talking to the Tattaglia family... right?
我认为我们可以一起做些生意
I think you and I can do business.
我需要像你这么壮的人
I need someone strong like you.
我听说你与柯里昂家族不和
I heard you are not happy with the Corleone family.
想加入我们吗？
Want to join me?
我能得到什么好处？
What's in it for me?
起薪五万元
$50,000 to start with.
还不坏
Not bad!
同意了？
Agreed?
汤姆·哈金  圣诞快乐
Tom! Tom Hagen. Merry Christmas.
我很高兴遇见你
I'm glad I run into you.
- 我想跟你聊聊  - 我没时间
- I wanna talk to you. - I haven't got time.
为我们拨点时间  军师  上车
Oh, make time, consigliere. Get in the car.
你担心什么？
What are you worried about?
我想杀你的话你早已死了
If I wanted to kill you, you'd be dead already.
上车
Get in.
稍候一下  弗雷多我买点水果
Fredo, I'm gonna buy some fruit.
好的  爸
Okay, Pa.
圣诞快乐  我要买些水果
Hi. Merry Christmas.I want some fruit over there.
那个给我 不 是那个
Gimme three of them.No, that one.
弗雷多
Fredo!
爸爸
Papa.Papa!
麦克  我若是修女你是否会更喜欢我
Would you like me better if I were a nun
就像小说中的角色你知道吗？
like in the story, you know?
不会
No.
若我是英格丽褒曼你是否会更喜欢我？
Then would you like me better if I were Ingrid Bergman?
这个想法不错
Now that's a thought.
麦克
Michael.
不  你若是英格丽褒曼我不会更喜欢你的
No, I would not like you better if you were Ingrid Bergman.
- 麦克  - 怎么回事？
- Mike- - What's the matter?
（维多柯里昂被谋杀）
上面没说他是死是活
They don't say if he's dead or alive.
- 山尼  我是麦克  - 麦克  你到哪去了？
- Sonny, Michael. - Michael, where you been?
- 他没事吧？  - 我们还不知道
Is he all right? We don't know yet. There's all kinds of stories.
他伤的很重  麦克
he was hit bad, Mikey.
- 你还在吗？  - 是的  我在这
- Are you there? - Yeah, I'm here.
- 你到哪去了？我很担心  - 汤姆没说我打过电话吗？
Where you been? I was worried. Didn't Tom tell you? I called.
听我说  回家来你应该在这陪妈妈的
No. Look, come home, kid. You should be with Mama, you hear?
好的
All right.
我的天啊
Oh, my God.
山尼
Sonny.
- 谁？  - 开门  我是克里曼沙
- Go. Who is it? - Open up. It's Clemenza.
又有你老头的消息了
There's more news about your old man.
街头谣传他已经死了
The word is out on the street he's already dead.
- 你是怎么回事？  - 山尼  别激动
Shut your mouth. What's the matter with you?Jesus Christ! Take it easy.
保利在哪？
- Where was Paulie?
保利病了  他整个冬天都病了
- Paulie was out sick. He's been sick all winter.
- 他病了几次？  - 病了三四次
- How many times he been sick? - Only maybe three, four times.
- 弗雷多并不想另找保镖  - 马上接他来
- I asked Freddy if he wants a different bodyguard.He said no. - Pick him up now.
我不管他病的有多重
I don't care how sick he is.
只要他还在呼吸我要你把他带到家父的房子去
If he's breathin', I want you to bring him to my father's house now.
现在  明白吗？现在
Understand? Now.
好  你要我派人到这边来吗？
You want me to send people here?
不用  去吧
No, just you and him. Go ahead.
我会派几个人到家里来
All right.I'm havin' a couple of our people come to the house.
- 你好  - 山尼·柯里昂吗？
- Hello? - Santino Corleone?
- 我就是  - 汤姆哈金在我们手上
- Yeah. - We have Tom hagen.
约三小时后我们会释放他
In about three hours, he'll be released with our proposition.
在你做任何事之前先听听他说的话
Listen to everything he has to say before you do anything.
木已成舟
What's done is done.
先别发怒  好吗？山尼
And don't lose that famous temper of yours, huh, Sonny?
不会的  我会等
No, I'll wait.
你的老板死了
Your boss is dead.
我知道你在家族中是不喜欢动武
I know you're not in the muscle end of the family
所以我不想要你感到害怕
so I don't want you to be scared.
我要你帮助柯里昂家族  还有帮我
I want you to help the Corleones and I want you to help me.
接了你约一小时后
We got him outside his office
我们已在他办公室外干掉他了
about an hour after we picked you up.
喝吧
Drink it.
现在全看你的了
So now it's up to you
让我与山尼和平解决一切
to make the peace between me and Sonny.
山尼对我的主意很热衷  不是吗？
Sonny was hot for my deal, wasn't he?
而且你知道那么做是对的
And you knew it was the right thing to do.
山尼会不惜一切的来追杀你
Sonny will come after you with everything he's got.
那会是他的第一个反应
That'll be his first reaction, sure.
所以要你去劝劝他
That's why you gotta talk some sense into him.
塔塔基利亚家族全力支持我
The Tattaglia family is behind me with all their people.
纽约其他的家族也会不惜一切防止全面的战争
The other New York families will go along with anything that will prevent a full-scale war.
让我们面对现实吧  汤姆
Let's face it,Tom
我们全都尊敬他
in all due respect
但教父已今非昔比愿他安息
the Don, rest in peace, was slippin'.
十年前我能对付他吗？
Ten years ago, could I have gotten to him?
但现在他已经死了
Well, now he's dead.
他死了  汤姆
He's dead, Tom
没什么能让他复生
and nothing can bring him back.
所以你得和山尼谈谈
So you gotta talk to Sonny.
也得说服两个大头目泰西欧及肥克里曼沙
You gotta talk to the caporegimes- that Tessio, that fat Clemenza.
那是笔好生意  汤姆
It's good business, Tom.
我试试看
I'll try.
但即使是山尼也阻止不了路卡
But even Sonny won't be able to call off Luca Brasi.
这个... 路卡让我来担心
Yeah. Well-Let me worry about Luca.
你只管说服山尼
You just talk to Sonny.
及他另外两个兄弟
And the other two kids.
- 我尽力而为  - 很好
- I'll do my best. - Good.
现在... 你可以走了
Now, you can go.
我不喜欢暴力  汤姆我是个生意人
I don't like violence, Tom. I'm a businessman.
流血代价太高了
Blood is a big expense.
他还活着
He's still alive.
他们打了他五枪  他还活着
They hit him with five shots, and he's still alive!
那对我是件坏事
Well, that's bad luck for me
若你不能谈成那档事对你也不是好事
and bad luck for you if you don't make that deal.
令堂在医院陪令尊
Your mother's over in the hospital with your father.
看起来他能度过难关谢天谢地
Looks like he's gonna pull through, thank God.
- 全是塔塔基利亚家族策划的  - 你认为如何？
- That's a lot of bad blood. - What do you think?
教父认为这是设计好的
It's too far. I think it's too personal.
- 你要把那些人全杀掉？  - 别插手这件事  麦克
- You gonna kill all those guys? - Stay out of it, Mickey. Do me a favor.
索拉索是关键除掉他一切就好办了
- Sollozzo's the key. You get rid of him, everything falls into line.
路卡呢？索拉索认为他可以控制路卡
What about Luca? Sollozzo didn't seem worried about Luca.
我不知道
I don't know.
如果路卡出卖我们我们就有大麻烦了
If Luca sold out, we're in a lot of trouble.
有人能与路卡连络上吗？
Has anyone been able to get in touch with Luca?
我试了一整夜  但没有人接
We've been tryin' all night. He might be shacked up.
麦克  帮我个忙打电话给路卡
Mick, Do me a favor. try him again.
他从不在外留宿他每次办完事会立刻回家
Luca never sleeps over with a broad.He always goes home when he's through.
汤姆  你是军师
Well, Tom, you're consigliere.
若是老头死了我们该怎么办？
What do we do if the old man dies, God forbid?
我们万一失去了老头
If we lose the old man
我们就会失去政界的连系
we lose our political contacts and half our strength.
纽约其他的家族为了避免长期的战争
The other New York families might wind up supporting Sollozzo
可能会联合支持索拉索
just to avoid a long destructive war.
现在是1946年了
This is almost 1946.
没有人想再流血了
Nobody wants bloodshed anymore.
若是令尊死了
If your father dies
就由你做决定了  山尼
you'll make the deal, Sonny.
你说来容易  那不是你父亲
That's easy for you to say. He's not your father.
我与你跟麦克对他来说都是儿子
I was as much a son to him as you or Mike.
什么事？
What is it?
保利  我叫你在外面守着
Hey, Paulie, I thought I told you to stay put.
大门的人说收到一包东西
The guy at the gates, they say they got a package.
泰西欧  去看看是什么
Yeah? Tessio, go see what it is.
你要我留在这？
You want me to hang around?
是的  留在这  你还好吧？
- Yeah, hang around.- You all right?
是的  我很好
Yeah,I'm fine.
有点吃的  你饿了吗？
Yeah? There's some food in the icebox. You hungry?
不  没关系的
No, it's all right. Thanks.
喝杯酒吧  一点白兰地能让你舒服点
- How 'bout a little brandy?- That's good to sweat it out.
- 好吧  - 去吧  孩子
- Sure. - Go ahead.
那或许是个好主意
That might be a good idea.
我要你立刻处置那个王八蛋
I want you to take care of that son of a bitch right away.
保利出卖了老头  那个混蛋
Paulie sold out the old man.
我不想再见到他
I don't wanna see him again.
这是你第一件先要解决的工作
Make that first thing on your list.
- 明白吗？  - 明白
- Understand? - Understood.
麦克  明天你带几个人...
Hey, Mickey, tomorrow you get a couple of guys.
到路卡的公寓去看看等他出现
Go to Luca's apartment. Wait for him to show up.
也许我们不该让麦克太直接涉入
Maybe we shouldn't get Mike mixed up in this too directly.
听我说... 待在家里接电话那会有大帮助的
Listen, hang around the house on the phone. It'll be a big help.
再试着打给路卡
Try Luca again. Go ahead.
- 这是什么？  - 那是西西里人的口信
- What the hell is this? - It's a Sicilian message.
那表示路卡布拉西与鱼同眠了
It means Luca Brasi sleeps with the fishes.
- 我现在要走了  - 你今晚几点会回家？
- I'm goin' now. - What time you gonna be home?
我不知道  也许会很晚
I don't know. Probably late.
- 别忘了油饼  - 知道了
- Don't forget the cannoli. - Yeah, yeah.
罗可  坐到另一边去
Rocco, sit on the other side.
你挡住后照镜了
You block the rearview mirror.
开始大发雷霆了
Sonny's runnin' wild.
他想要跟对手开战了
He's thinkin' of goin' to the mattresses already.
我们得在西区找个地方藏匿
We gotta find a spot over on the West Side.
你试试西43街309号
We'll try 309 West 43rd Street.
- 你知道西区有何好地方吗？  - 我想想看
- You know any good spots on the West Side? - Yeah, I'll think about it.
你开车的时候想想好吗？
- Think while you're drivin'.
我这个月要找一天到纽约去
I wanna hit New York sometime this month.
倒车出去时留意小孩子
And watch out for the kids when you're backin' out.
保利  我要你到39街去
Paulie, I want you to go down 39th Street. Colosanto's.
去买18个垫子
Pick up 18 mattresses for the guys to sleep.
然后把帐单拿给我
Bring me the bill.
确定要干净的
- Yeah, all right. - Make sure they're clean.
因为我们要在那待段长时间
Those guys are gonna be stuck up in there for a long time.
它们是干净的  他们说消毒过
They're clean. They told me they exterminate them.
消毒  用那个字很不好
''Exterminate''? That's a bad word to use.
消毒  听听这个家伙
Exterminate. Get this guy.
小心点  我们才不会为你消毒
See how we don't exterminate you.
那真是好笑
- Youse funny, or what? - Hey, Paulie?
停到路旁去好吗？我要小便
Pull over.I gotta take a leak.
把枪留下
Leave the gun.
把油饼给我
Take the cannoli.
麦克...
Hey, Mike!
怎么啦?
Yeah?
你的电话
You're wanted on the telephone.
- 是谁？  - 女孩子
- Who is it? - It's some girl.
- 你好  凯  - 令尊还好吗？
- Hello, Kay? - How's your father?
他很好  他能活过来
He's good. He's gonna make it.
我爱你
I love you.
- 麦克  - 是  我知道
- Michael? - Yeah, I know.
告诉我你爱我
Tell me you love me.
我不能说
I can't talk.
你不能说吗？
Can't you say it?
我们今晚见
Yeah, I'll see you tonight.
麦克  你为何不说你爱她
Why don't you tell that nice girl you love her?
我全心全意的爱你
I love you with all o' my heart!
我若不快点见到你  我会死的
If I don't see you again a-soon, I'm-a gonna die!
到这来  孩子  学点东西
Come over here, kid. Learn somethin'.
有一天你也许得为20个男人煮饭
You might have to cook for 20 guys someday.
一开始先倒点油  炸大蒜
You see? You start out with a little bit of oil.Then you fry some garlic.
然后放番茄  炒一下
Then you throw in some tomatoes, some tomato paste.
别让它粘锅底
You fry it. You make sure it doesn't stick.
煮开了之后  加入香肠及肉丸
When you got it to a boil, shove in all your sausage and meatballs.
再加一点点酒
And a little bit of wine.
以及...
And
一点点糖
a little bit of sugar.
那是我的秘方
And that's my trick.
你别说废话了
Why don't you cut the crap?
我有更重要的事要让你去做
I got more important things for you to do.
保利呢？
How's Paulie?
保利  你再也见不到他了
Won't see him no more.
你要去哪？
Where you going?
到城里去
To the city.
派保镖跟他一起去
Send some bodyguards with him.
我只是去医院看爸爸
I'm just going to see Pop.
我不管  派人跟他一起去
Send somebody with him.
他不会有事的  索拉索知道他是''平民''
He'll be all right. Sollozzo knows he's a civilian.
- 小心点  - 是的
- All right. Be careful, huh? - Yes, sir.
还是派人跟他一起去
Send somebody with him anyway.
- 我得走了  - 我能与你一起去吗？
I have to go.Can I go with you?
不  凯  那里有刑警还有记者
No, Kay. There's gonna be detectives there.People from the press.
我在车上等你
I'll ride in a cab.
我不要你卷入这件事
I don't want you to get involved.
我何时能再见到你？
When will I see you again?
回新罕布夏去
Go back to New Hampshire
我打电话去你父母家找你
and I'll call you at your parents' house.
我何时才能再见到你？麦克
When will I see you again, Michael?
我不知道
I don't know.
你在这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
现在不是探病时间
You're not supposed to be here now.
我是麦克柯里昂
I'm Michael Corleone.
这是家父
This is my father.
这里没人  守卫到哪去了？
There's nobody here. What happened to the guards?
令尊访客太多妨碍了医院的作业
Your father just had too many visitors.They interfered with hospital service.
警察在十分钟前要他们离去了
The police made them leave about ten minutes ago.
请帮我接长滩45620
Get me Long Beach 4-5-6-2-0, please.
护士  等一下  先别走
Nurse, wait a minute. Stay here.
山尼  我是麦克  我在医院
Sonny, Michael. I'm at the hospital.
听着  我很晚才到这儿这没有人
Listen. I got here late. There's nobody here.
泰西欧的人不在也没有刑警  没有人
Nobody. No Tessio's men, no detectives, nobody.
爸爸单独一个人在这
- Pop is all alone. - Don't panic. We'll send somebody.
- 别惊慌  - 我不会惊慌
- Don't panic. - I won't panic.
我很抱歉  但你必须离去
I'm sorry, but you will have to leave.
你帮我把家父移去另一间房
You and I are gonna move my father to another room.
现在你是否能把这个拆开
Can you disconnect those tubes
我来推病床
so we can move the bed out?
- 那是不可能的  - 你认识家父吗？
- That's out of the question. - Do you know my father?
他们会来杀了他  懂吗？
Men are coming here to kill him.You understand?
现在请你帮我忙
Now, help me, please.
- 你是谁？  - 我是安索  那个糕饼师
- Who are you? - I am Enzo- the baker.
- 你还记得我吧？  - 安索
- You remember me? - Enzo?
是的  我是安索
Yes, Enzo.
你最好离开这  安索这里会有麻烦
You better get out of here, Enzo.There's gonna be trouble.
若是有麻烦  我留在这帮你
If there is trouble, I stay here to help you-
为了令尊
For your father. For your father.
好吧  听我说
All right, listen.
在医院大门外面等我  好吗？
Wait for me outside, in front of the hospital.All right?
我马上出来  快去
I'll be out in a minute. Go ahead.
好的...
OK.
好好休息吧  爸
Just lie here, Pop.
我会照料你的
I'll take care of you now.
我和你在一起
I'm with you now.
把这个丢掉
Get rid of these.
到这来
Come here.
把手放在口袋里就像你有把枪
Put your hand in your pocket like you have a gun.
你不会有事的
You'll be all right.
You'll be okay.
你做的很好
You did good.
这是干什么？
What's this for?
我以为把你们这些混混全关住了
I thought I got all you guinea hoods locked up.
你在这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
守家父的人是怎么回事？
What happened to the men who were guarding my father, Captain?
你这个小混蛋  竟敢管我的事
Why, you little punk. Don't you tell me my business!
是我把那些人全赶走的
I pulled them guys off of here.
你马上离开这医院
You get out of here and stay away from this hospital.
除非你派人守护家父否则我不会走
I'm not moving until you put some guards around my father's room.
菲尔  把他带回去
Phil, take him in.
那孩子是清白的  队长
The kid's clean, Captain. He's a war hero.
他是个服役荣归的英雄从未和黑手党混在一起
- He's a war hero. He's never been...
该死的  我说把他带回去
Goddamn it, I said take him in.
索拉索付你多少钱来陷害家父？
What's the Turk paying you to set up my father, Captain?
把他抓牢  让他站稳
Take ahold of him. Stand him up. Stand him up straight.
我是柯里昂家的律师
I'm the attorney for the Corleone family.
这些人是私家侦探
These men are private detectives hired
雇来保护维多柯里昂的
to protect Vito Corleone.
他们有携带武器的执照
They're licensed to carry firearms.
若是你干预  我们明早法庭见
If you interfere, you'll have to appear before a judge in the morning and show cause.
好了  让他走
All right, let him go.
走吧
Come on.
这些新面孔是怎么回事？
What's with all the new faces?
我们现在需要他们
Gonna need 'em now.
经过医院的事之后山尼气疯了
After the hospital thing, Sonny got mad.
我们今晨四点干掉了布诺塔塔基利亚
We hit Bruno Tattaglia at 4:00 this morning.
老天爷
Jesus Christ.
这里看起来像是座城堡
Looks like a fortress around here.
街上一天24小时都有一百个枪手在巡逻
A hundred button men on the street, 24 hours a day.
那土耳其人敢露出一根汗毛就挂了
That Turk shows one hair on his ass, he's dead. Believe me.
麦克  到这里来  让我看看你
Hey, Michael, come here. Let me look at you.
你漂亮极了  漂亮极了
You look beautiful. Just beautiful. You're gorgeous.
你们听我说
Hey, listen to this.
那土耳其人想谈判
The Turk, he wants to talk.
那王八蛋紧张了
Imagine the nerve on this son of a bitch.
昨晚整我们  今天想和谈
Craps out last night, he wants a meeting today.
- 他怎么说？  - 他怎么说？
- What'd he say? - What did he say?
他要我们派麦克去
He wants us to send Michael to hear the proposition.
并保证那条件好到我们不会拒绝
And the promise is that the deal is so good that we can't refuse.
那布诺塔塔基利亚呢？
What about Bruno Tattaglia?
那是条件的一部分
That's part of the deal.
他作为对家父挨枪的补偿
Bruno cancels out what they did to my father.
山尼  我们该听听他们怎么说
Sonny, we ought to hear what they have to say.
不  不再听了  军师
No more. Not this time, Consigliere.
不再和谈  不再讨论不再上索拉索的当
No more meetings, no discussions, no more Sollozzo tricks.
你去跟他们说  我要索拉索
You give them one message- I want Sollozzo.
否则我们就开战
If not, it's all-out war. We go to the mattresses.
山尼  其他家族不会支持的
Some of the other families won't sit still for a war.
叫他们把索拉索交给我
- Then they hand me Sollozzo. - Your father wouldn't like this.
山尼  令尊不会喜欢的这是生意  不能感情用事
This is business, not personal.
那我父亲就该挨枪了？
They shot my father.
即使是令尊挨枪也是生意
Even shooting your father was business,
不是个人的事  山尼
not personal, Sonny.
那生意必须要停  行吗？
Well, then business will have to suffer.
听着  帮我个忙  汤姆
And do me a favor, Tom-
别再建议我如何让事情过去
No more advice on how to patch things up.
只要帮我赢  好吗？
Just help me win, please. All right?
我查出了打断麦克下巴那麦克劳斯基队长的事
I found out about this McCluskey who broke Mike's jaw.
他怎么样？
What about him?
他肯定在索拉索的规费名单中  而且是很大一笔钱
He's definitely on Sollozzo's payroll, and for big money.
麦克劳斯基是索拉索的保镖
McCluskey has agreed to be the Turk's bodyguard.
你必须要了解  山尼
What you have to understand, Sonny
当索拉索跟警察队长勾搭上时
is that while Sollozzo's being guarded like this
没人可以碰他了
he is invulnerable.
过去从没人胆敢干掉纽约警官
Nobody has ever gunned down a New York police captain. Never.
那会是个大灾难
It would be disastrous.
所有五大家族都会追杀你  山尼
All the five families would come after you.
柯里昂家族会被孤立
The Corleone family would be outcast.
即使是老头的政治保护都会消失
Even the old man's political protection would run for cover.
拜托你
So do me a favor.
别轻举妄动
Take this into consideration.
好吧  我们等
All right, we'll wait.
我们不能等
We can't wait.
Can't wait.
不管索拉索答应什么  他会杀了爸爸的
I don't care what Sollozzo says about a deal.He's gonna kill Pop. That's it.
那是他的关键
That's the key for him.
必须干掉索拉索
Got to get Sollozzo.
麦克说的对
Mike is right.
那个谈判就没有必要了
Let me ask you something first.
这个麦克劳斯基呢？
What about this McCluskey?
我们要拿这个条子怎么办？
What do we do with this cop?
他们想跟我见面  对吧？
They want to have a meeting with me, right?
那会是我 麦克劳斯基及索拉索
It will be me McCluskey and Sollozzo.
我们来安排这次会面
Let's set the meeting.
我们查清楚见面地点在哪里
Get our informers to find out where it's going to be held.
必须是公开场所  酒吧或餐厅
We insist it's a public place- a bar, a restaurant.
人多的地方对我比较安全
Someplace where there's people, so I feel safe.
我与他们一见面他们会搜身  对吧
They're gonna search me when I first meet them, right?
那么我身上不能有武器
So I can't have a weapon on me then.
若克里曼沙能想出一个办法
But if Clemenza can figure a way
能预先把武器放在那
to have a weapon planted there for me
那我就能杀了他们两个
then I'll kill them both.
你要怎么做？乖乖的大学生
What are you gonna do? Nice college boy, huh?
你不是不想和家族中的事混在一块吗？
Didn't want to get mixed up in the family business.
现在因为他打了你你就想干掉他？
Now you want to gun down a police captain?
你以为这里是什么？军队吗？
Why? 'Cause he slapped you in the face a little bit?
在一哩以外开枪打他们？
Do you think this is the army, where you shoot them a mile away?
你必须离这么近  砰一声
You gotta get up close, like this and-
他们的脑浆会溅到你身上
You blow their brains all over your nice Ivy League suit. Come here.
- 山尼...   - 你太感情用事了
You're taking this very personal.
汤姆  这是公事而他却感情用事
Tom, this is business, and this man is taking it very, very personal.
谁说不能杀条子的？
Where does it say you can't kill a cop?
- 别这样  麦克  - 汤姆  慢着
- Come on, Mikey. - Tom, wait a minute.
他是个跟毒品买卖有关的条子
I'm talking about a cop that's mixed up in drugs.
他是个不诚实的条子
I'm talking about a dishonest cop, a crooked cop
和毒贩混在一起终于得到报应
who got mixed up in the rackets and got what was coming to him.
那是个好极了的故事
That's a terrific story.
报社不是有我们的人吗？
We have newspaper people on the payroll, don't we, Tom?
他们也许对那故事有兴趣
They might like a story like that.
他们也许  只是也许
They might. They just might.
不是感情用事  山尼  纯粹是公事
It's not personal, Sonny. It's strictly business.
做过表面处理了  追踪不到的
It's as cold as they come. Impossible to trace,
不用担心指纹
so you don't worry about prints, Mike.
我在扳机和手把上贴了特殊胶布
I put a special tape on the trigger and the butt.
来  试试看
Here. Try it.
怎么了？扳机太紧了？
What's the matter, the trigger too tight?
我的耳朵好辛苦
- My ears. - I left it noisy.
我没安装消声器那样才能吓走旁观的人
That way it scares pain-in-the-ass innocent bystanders away.
好了  你杀了他们两个
All right, you shot them both.
接下来你怎么办？
Now what do you do?
坐下吃完我的晚餐
Sit down, finish my dinner.
别开玩笑
Come on, kid. Don't fool around.
就让你的手垂下  让枪滑掉
Just let your hand drop to your side and let the gun slip out.
每个人都认为你还拿着枪
Everybody will still think you got it.
他们会瞪着你的脸  麦克
They're gonna be staring at your face, Mike
所以快步离开那地方但不要跑
so walk out of the place real fast, but you don't run.
别直视任何人但也不要看其他地方
Don't look nobody directly in the eye, but don't look away, either.
他们会怕的不敢瞪你  相信我  不必担心
They're gonna be scared stiff of you, believe me so don't worry about nothing.
你若可以全身而退
You know, you're gonna turn out all right.
可以休个长假  到哪里都可以
You take a long vacation, nobody knows where
而我们会处理善后
and we're gonna catch the hell.
- 你认为后果会有多糟？  - 他妈的蛮糟的
How bad do you think it's gonna be? Pretty goddamn bad.
可能所有的家族会联合对付我们
Probably all the other families will line up against us.
那没关系的
That's all right.
每五年或十年都会发生一次
These things gotta happen every five years or so. Ten years.
害群之马必须要除掉
Helps to get rid of the bad blood.
上一次到现在已有十年了
Been ten years since the last one.
要先发制人
You gotta stop them at the beginning
就像要在慕尼黑制止希特勒一样
like they should have stopped Hitler at Munich.
他们容忍了希特勒  麻烦就大了
They should have never let him get away with that.They was just asking for big trouble.
知道吗？麦克
You know, Mike,
我们都以你为荣  你是个英雄
we was all proud of you being a hero and all.
你父亲也是
Your father too.
没有任何线索  什么都没有
Nothing. Not a hint. Absolutely nothing.
索拉索的人也不知在哪里会面
Even Sollozzo's people don't know where the meeting will be held.
我有多少时间？
How much time do we have?
一小时半以后他们在达西路口接你上车
in an hour and a half- exactly an hour and a half.
我们派个人追踪他们
We could put a tail on them, see how it turns out.
索拉索会在街上乱转甩掉我们的人
Sollozzo'll lose our ass going around the block.
来找我们谈判的人呢？
What about the negotiator?
他在那边和我的手下玩纸牌
He's over at my place playing pinochle with a couple of my men.
他很高兴  我们在让他赢
He's happy. They're letting him win.
对麦克太危险了
It's too much of a risk for Mike.
山尼  也许我们该取消
Maybe we ought to call it off.
要麦克平安回来
The negotiator keeps playing cards
我们才会让那个人走的
until Mike's back safe and sound.
何不干脆干掉车上的人呢？
Why doesn't he blast who's ever in the goddamn car?
太危险了  他们会注意的
Too dangerous. They'll be looking for that.
索拉索也许根本就不在车上
Sollozzo might not even be in the car, Sonny.
我来接
I got it.
布朗区的路易士餐厅
Louis Restaurant in the Bronx.
可靠吗？
Is it reliable?
麦克劳斯基的分局里有我的人
That's my man in McCluskey's precinct.
队长必须24小时待命
A police captain's got to be on call 24 hours a day.
他八点到十点会去那里
He signed out at that number between 8:00 and 10:00.
有谁知道那个地方
Anybody know this joint?
我知道
Yeah, sure. I do.
对我们太理想了
It's perfect for us.
家庭餐厅  食物精美
A small family place, good food.
各吃各的  太理想了
Everyone minds his business. It's perfect.
彼得  那儿有个旧式马桶
Pete, they got an old-fashioned toilet-
你知道就是水箱有吊链的那种
You know, the box and the chain thing.
我们或许可把枪用胶带绑在那
We might be able to tape the gun behind it.
好的  麦克  你去餐厅
All right. Mike, you go to the restaurant.
你一面吃一面聊  别紧张
You eat, you talk for a while, you relax.
也可以使对方轻松下来
You make them relax.
然后你站起来去上厕所
Then you get up and go take a leak.
你得先征求对方同意再去
No, better still, you ask for permission to go.
回来时就开枪
And when you come back, you come out blasting.
别失误  对准头颅各开两枪
And don't take any chances. Two shots in the head apiece.
听着  我要一个好手去藏枪
Now, listen. I want somebody good- and I mean very good- to plant that gun.
我不希望我弟弟出来时
I don't want him coming out
手无寸铁
with just his dick in his hands.
枪会在那的
The gun will be there.
你开车送他  事后再接他回来
All right, listen. You drive him and you pick him up after the job.
来吧  我们动身了
Come on. Let's move.
他告诉过你事成之后立刻丢枪吗？
Did he tell you to drop the gun right away?
几百万次了
Yeah, a million times.
切记  朝每人头部开两枪一出厕所后就打
Don't forget- two shots apiece in the head as soon as you come out the door.
你们认为要多久我才能回家？
How long do you think it'll be before I can come back?
至少得一年  麦克
At least a year, Mike.
我会转告妈你临走前不能去看她
Listen, I'll square with Mom you not seeing her before you leave
我会告诉你女朋友的
I'll get a message to that girlfriend when the time is right.
保重
Take care.
保重  麦克
See you, Mike.
我很高兴你来了  麦克
I'm glad you came, Mike.
希望我们能把事情谈妥
I hope we can straighten everything out.
这种事太可怕了  我并不希望发生这种事
This is terrible. It's not the way I wanted things to go at all.
不该发生这种事的
It should have never happened.
我会在今晚解决一切
I want to straighten everything out tonight.
我不希望我爸烦心
I don't want my father bothered anymore.
会解决的  麦克
He won't be, Mike.
我以我孩子之名发誓
I swear on my children he won't be.
不过谈的时候  你得坦诚才行
But you got to keep an open mind when we talk.
希望你不像令兄的坏脾气
I hope you're not a hothead like your brother Sonny.
简直没办法和他谈正事
You can't talk business with him.
（意大利文）
他是个好孩子
He's a good kid.
那晚的事我很抱歉  麦克
I'm sorry about the other night, Mike.
我得搜你的身  转过来
I gotta frisk you, so turn around, huh?
跪在椅子上  脸向我
On your knees, facing me.
我想我干这行已经嫌老了
I guess I'm getting too old for my job.
太多话了
Too grouchy.
受不了别人的激怒  你该明白吧
Can't stand the aggravation.You know how it is.
他没带家伙
He's clean.
到新泽西去？
We're going to Jersey?
也许
Maybe.
漂亮极了  路
Nice work, Lou.
（路易士餐厅）
这里的意大利菜味道还可以吧？
How's the Italian food in this restaurant?
很棒
Good.
试试这里的小牛肉是本市最棒的
Try the veal. It's the best in the city.
给我来一份
I'll have it.
快
Go ahead.
好了
Allright,
我要和麦克用意大利文交谈
I'm gonna speak Italian to Mike.
请便
Go ahead.
我对现在的形势很遗憾
你当真这样想?
我跟你父亲之间纯粹是生意上的问题
我很尊敬你父亲
但你父亲的思路已经过时了
你一定要知道一件事
我也是个有荣誉感的人
不用再提这些...  我已经知道了
你知道?
我已经向塔塔利亚家族求援了
目前我确信我们将能够达成一个协议
我要和平
让我们把所有的仇恨和不快抛到脑后吧
但是你玩得...  这样如何
我想说的是
What I want
对我而言  最重要的是
what's most important to me,
保证家父的性命安全
is that I have a guarantee:No more attempts on my father's life.
你要我怎么保证？麦克
What guarantees could I give you?
我也是惊弓之鸟
I am the hunted one.
我也失手
I missed my chance.
你太看重我了  孩子
You think too much of me, kid.
我没有那么精明
I'm not that clever.
我想要的只是息战而已
All I want is a truce.
我必须要上厕所  可以吗？
I have to go to the bathroom. Is that all right?
想去就去吧
You gotta go, you gotta go.
我搜过了  他没带家伙
I frisked him. He's clean.
别去太久
Don't take too long.
我搜过好几千人了
I've frisked a thousand young punks.
感觉好些了吧?
恩
麦克  你知道吗  你是个意大利人  就像你父亲
你父亲已经病了
等他好些了  我们开个会
我们要收拾局面
得结束这样的敌对局面
（警方追捕警察杀手）
（本市黑道瓦解）
（警察队长与毒贩勾结）
（黑社会头子巴西尼接受警方盘问）
（黑社会大火拚）
（黑社会大亨维多柯里昂返家）
好了  转进来
Hey, come on.
好了  你接手
Joe, you take over.
我爱你  爷爷
I love you, Grandpa.
对不起  爸  他还不认识你
I'm sorry, Pa. He doesn't know you yet.
小家伙  念给爷爷听
Here you are, big guy. Give it to Grandpa.
好  我祝你早日康复  爷爷我希望能快点见到你
''I hope you get well, Grandpa and I wish I would see you soon.
爱你的孙子  法兰克
Love, your grandson, Frank.''
多乖巧
走吧  到外面去
Go with your mother.
把他们带到楼下去吧
Go ahead. Take 'em downstairs.
妈
走吧  卡洛  你也是
Go on, Carlo. You too.
走吧
Go on.
你要烤鸡吗？那是他最喜欢的
I got chicken cacciatore for you, sweetheart.
我知道  但他能吃多少呢？
But how much can you eat?
你怎么了？卡洛
What's the matter with you, Carlo?
闭嘴  去摆桌子吧
Shut up and set the table.
自从麦克劳斯基被杀后
Since McCluskey's killing
警方瓦解了我们多数业务
the police have been cracking down on most of our operations.
其他的家族也是一样
And also the other families'.
牺牲很多
Been a lot of bad blood.
他们攻击我们
They hit us,
我们反击
so we hit them back.
透过我们报社中的连系  我们提供了不少内幕
Through our contacts in the newspapers we've been able to put out a lot of material
很多麦克劳斯基跟毒贩索拉索勾结的事
about McCluskey being linked with Sollozzo in the drug rackets.
所以风声已经没有那么紧了
See, things are starting to loosen up.
还有我派弗雷多去拉斯维加斯
Dad, I'm sending Fredo to Las Vegas
在洛杉矶的法兰西斯科阁下会给予他保护
under the protection of Don Francesco of L.A.
- 我要他休息一会儿  - 我要去学赌场的事
I want him to rest. I'm going to learn the casino business.
麦克在哪？
Where is Michael?
杀索拉索的是麦克
It was Michael who killed Sollozzo.
不过他很安全  别担心
But he's safe. We're starting to work
我们会把他弄回来的
to bring him back now.
你查出塔塔基利亚躲在哪儿没？
I want you to find out where that little pimp Tattaglia is hiding.
我要他的命  现在
I want his ass now- right now.
- 听我说  山尼  - 什么事？
- Hey, Sonny. - What?
现在局势才刚刚缓和下来
Things are starting to loosen up a little bit.
你若去追塔塔基利亚
If you go after Tattaglia,
又会引起一场大战的
all hell's going to break loose.
等事情平静一点让爸爸去协调
Let the smoke clear. Pop can negotiate.
不  爸爸在身体好转之前什么都不能做
No, Pop can't do nothing till he's better.
我要决定什么对我们最有利
I'm gonna decide-
好的  可是你那场火拚使我们损失很多
All right, but your war's costing us a lot of money.
没有任何进帐  我们不能做事
Nothing's coming in. We can't do business.
他们也不行  别担心
Neither can they. Don't worry about it.
- 他们没有我们损失那么大  - 请你别担心这点
- We can't afford a stalemate. - No more stalemate.
我会以宰了那老混蛋来做结束
I'm gonna end it by killing that old bastard.
是  你现在名声很大你一定很得意吧
You're getting a great reputation. I hope you're enjoying it.
依照我叫你做的去做
Do what I tell you to do!
该死的  我若有个西西里人来当我的战略军师
Goddamn it, if I had a wartime consigliere- a Sicilian-
我就不会落到这种地步了
I wouldn't be in this shape!
爸爸有杰安可  看看我有什么？
Pop had Genco. Look what I got.
对不起  我不是有意的
I'm sorry. I didn't mean that.
妈妈煮了晚餐  今天是星期天
Mom made a little dinner. It's Sunday.
黑人对我们哈林区的银行新政策非常满意
Niggers are having a good time with our policy banks up there in Harlem.
开着新凯迪拉克我先帮他们付一半的钱
Driving them new Cadillacs, paying 50? on a bet.
从他们开始赚钱时我就知道这会发生
I knew that was gonna happen as soon as they started making big money.
爸爸从来不在餐桌上当着孩子们谈他的公事
Papa never talked business at the table in front of the kids.
- 闭嘴  康妮 - 不准你叫她闭嘴  知道吗？
- Shut up, Connie. - Don't you ever tell her to shut up. You got that?
别干预
Santino, don't interfere.
山尼 汤姆吃过饭后  我想与你们谈谈
Sonny, Tom, I'd like to talk to you, maybe after dinner.
- 我对家族也许能帮很多的  - 我们不在餐桌上讨论公事
I could be doing more for the family. We don't discuss business at the table.
我向你致敬  汤马西诺阁下
I kiss your hand, Don Tommasino.
麦克
Mike
你为何离房子那么远？
I kiss your hand, Don Tommasino.
你可知万一你出了事  我要向令尊负责的
You know I'm responsible to your father for your life.
保镖们都在这
The bodyguards are here.
还是十分危险
It's still dangerous...
我听纽约的山提诺说的
We've heard from Santino in New York...
你的敌人知道你在这了
Your enemies know you're here.
山提诺有没有说我何时能回去？
Did Santino say when I can go back?
还不行
Not yet.
目前是不可能的
It's out of the question.
谢谢
Thanks
你现在要去哪里？
Where are you going now?
柯里昂村
坐我的车去
Take my car.
我想走路
I want to walk.
小心点
Be careful.
麦克  柯里昂村到了
所有的男人都到哪去了？
Where have all the men gone?
他们全都在战争中死了
They're all dead from vendettas.
这里是死者的姓名
There are the names of the dead.
我的老天  好一个美女
Mamma mia what a beauty.
你好像中邪了一样
I think you got hit by the thunderbolt.
麦克
Mike
在西西里  女人比猎枪还危险
In Sicily women are more dangerous than shotguns.
打猎有收获吗？
Did you have a good hunt?
你认识这一带所有的女孩吗？
You know all the girls around here?
我们看到几位真正的美人
We saw some real beauties.
其中一位让我们的朋友触电了
One of them struck our friend like a thunderbolt.
她可真够骚了
She would tempt the devil himself.
她全身上下都很美
Really put together.
那么漂亮的头发  嘴
Such hair, such mouth!
这一带的女孩都很美而且很贞洁
The girls around here are beautiful... but virtuous.
这个穿着紫色衣服
This one had a purple dress...
头发上绑着紫色的缎带
And a purple ribbon in her hair.
看起来像希腊人而非意大利人
A type more Greek than Italian.
你认识她吗？
Do you know her?
不认识
No
在本镇没有那样子的女孩
There's no girl like that in this town.
我的天  我明白了
My God, I understand!
有什么不对了？
What's wrong?
我们走
Let's go.
是他女儿
It's his daughter.
叫他出来
Tell him to come here.
法布利奇欧  你翻译
Fabrizio, you translate.
是的  先生
Yes sir.
我若冒犯了你  我道歉
I apologize if I offended you.
我初到贵地
I'm a stranger in this country
我无意冒犯你和令嫒
and I meant no disrespect to you or your daughter.
我是个美国人到西西里来避风头
I'm an American hiding in Sicily.
我的名字是麦克柯里昂
My name is Michael Corleone.
有人会为了钱而出卖我在此的消息
There are people who would pay a lot of money for that information.
但那样令嫒会失去父亲
But then your daughter would lose a father
而不是得到一位丈夫
instead of gaining a husband.
我想认识你女儿
I want to meet your daughter
但要在你的同意下
with your permission
及在你的家人的监督之下
and under the supervision of your family
我绝对是诚心诚意
with all respect.
星期天早上到我家来  我叫维提
Come to my house Sunday morning. My name is Vitelli.
谢谢
她叫什么名字？
What's her name?
艾波洛妮亚
很美的名字
这是小女艾波洛妮亚
这位是麦克柯里昂先生
谢谢
等我回来干你
I'll knock you dizzy.
废话少说
Save it for the library.
来吧  我们得去接我妹妹
Come on. We've got to pick up my sister.
怎么了？
What's matter?
- 是我的错  - 他在哪？
- It was my fault! - Where is he?
山尼  拜托  是我的错
Sonny, please. It was my fault. I hit him.
山尼  是我的错  是我先开始打他的
I started a fight with him. Please, Sonny.
求你  山尼  我先打他的
I'm sorry.
- 我...   - 好了
我只是叫医生来看你  好吗？
I'm just gonna get a doctor to come and take a look at you.
山尼  求你别动手
Sonny, please don't do anything.
好  你是怎么了？我会怎么做？
What's the matter with you? What am I gonna do?
我会让你肚里的孩子做遗腹子吗？
Am I gonna make that baby an orphan before he's born?
好了吗？
All right?
这些家伙把洋基队打得惨兮兮
Still betting the Yankees pretty heavy?
叫他们不要再接受投注了
Tell him to stop taking action, all right?
我们上周末输的钱够多了
You lost enough money last weekend to me.
卡洛  到这来...
Carlo, come here.
你再碰我妹妹一下我会杀了你
You touch my sister again, I'll kill you.
（意大利文）
没想到你会来  凯怎么不先打个电话来
Weren't expecting you. You should call.
我有打  我写过信也打过电话
Yes, well, I have. I've tried writing and calling.
我要和麦克连络
Now, I wanna reach Michael.
没有人知道他在哪
Nobody knows where he is.
我们知道他没事  但仅此而已
We know he's all right, but that's all.
- 怎么了？  - 那是件车祸但没有人受伤
- What was that? - That's an accident. But nobody was hurt.
汤姆
Tom.
请你把这封信交给麦克好吗？
Would you give this letter to Michael, please?
我若接受了法院可以证实我晓得他在哪里
if I accepted that in a court of law they could prove I have knowledge of his whereabouts.
你有耐心点  凯他会与你连络的  好吗？
Just be patient. He'll get in touch with you.
我让我的计程车走了我是否能进去打电话叫一辆？
I let my cab go. Can I come in to call another one?
来吧  对不起  来吧
Come on. I'm sorry. Come on.
卡洛在吗？
Is Carlo there?
- 你是哪位？  - 我是卡洛的朋友
- Who's this? - This is a friend of Carlo's.
你告诉他我今晚没空
Would you tell him that I can't make it tonight until later?
贱人
Bitch.
- 晚餐在桌上了  - 我还不饿
- Dinner's on the table. - I'm not hungry yet.
- 晚餐在桌上快凉了  - 我有约了
Your food is on the table. It's getting cold.
你刚叫我给你做晚餐的
- I'll eat out later. - You told me to make you dinner.
- 滚开好吗？  - 你才滚开
Hey, vaffancolo, eh? I'll vaffanculo you!
你这个意大利婊子
This little guinea brat.
好  全都打破了
That's it. Break it all,
你这被宠坏的女娃  全打破了
you spoiled guinea brat. Break it all!
你为何不把那个妓女带回家吃晚饭？
Why don't you bring your whore home for dinner?
也许我会  有何不可？
Maybe I will. Why not?
现在把它清干净
Now clean it up!
我不要  我才不要
Like hell I will!
清干净  贱人
Clean it up, you guinea spoiled brat!
清干净  我说清干净
Clean it up! I said clean it up!
清干净
Clean it up!
不
No.
清干净  他妈的
You son of a bitch!
清干净...
Clean it up!
清干净
来  杀我  像你爸一样当凶手
Come on, now! Kill me! Be a murderer like your father!
来吧  你们姓柯里昂的全是凶手
- All you Corleones are murderers! - I hate you!
来吧  贱人
- Come on! - I'll kill you!
来吧  杀我  滚
Kill me! Get up! Get out of here!
- 我恨你  - 快点  否则我要杀你了
- I hate you! - Now I'll kill you.
你这意大利贱货
You guinea brat, you.
滚出来
Get out here!
不
No!
康妮  怎么回事？
Connie, what's the matter?
我听不见你说的  什么事？
I can't hear you. What is it?
康妮  说大声点  孩子在哭
Talk louder. The baby's crying.
山提诺  我听不懂  我不明白
Santino, I can't understand- I don't know.
什么事？康妮？
Yeah, Connie.
听我说  你在那等着
Listen, you wait there.
不  你在那等着就对了
No, you just wait there.
王八蛋
That son of a bitch.
- 怎么回事？  - 王八蛋
Sonny, what's the matter?
快开门  站起来
Open the goddamn gate. Get off your ass.
山尼
Sonny
- 山尼  - 滚开
- Sonny, come on! - Get out of here!
跟他一起去  快点
Go after him. Go on.
王八蛋  快点...
Son of a bitch. Come on! Come on!
把那个给我
Give me a drop.
我太太在楼上哭
My wife is crying upstairs.
我听见车子到家里来
I hear cars coming to the house.
我的好军师
Consigliere of mine
所有人都知道  只有我毫不知情
I think you should tell your Don what everyone seems to know.
我没告诉妈任何事
I didn't tell Mama anything.
我正预备去叫醒你  并告诉你
I was about to come up and wake you just now and tell you.
但你需要先喝杯酒
But you needed a drink first.
现在你喝过酒了
Now you've had your drink.
他们在收费站杀了山尼
They shot Sonny on the causeway.
他死了
He's dead.
我不要追查此事
I want no inquiries made.
我不要复仇
I want no acts of vengeance.
我要你安排一次会议
I want you to arrange a meeting
与五大家族的族长
with the heads of the five families.
这场火拚该终止了
This war stops now.
打电话给包纳萨拉
Call Bonasera.
我现在需要他了
We need him now.
我是汤姆哈金
This is Tom Hagen calling for Vito Corleone
维多柯里昂要我打这个电话
at his request.
你欠教父一次人情
Now, you owe your Don a service.
他相信你会回报他的
he has no doubt that you will repay it.
他在一小时后会到你的殡仪馆去
Now, he will be at your funeral parlor in one hour.
请在那等待
Be there to greet him.
我的朋友
Well, my friend
你预备为我服务了吗？
are you ready to do me this service?
是的  但你要我怎么做？
Yes. What do you want me to do?
我要你尽你一切的力量和技巧好好为他化妆
I want you to use all your powers and all your skills.
我不要他母亲看到他这个样子
I don't want his mother to see him this way.
看看他们是怎么对我的孩子？
Look how they massacred my boy.
教你英语会安全一点
It's safer to teach you English!
我会英语
I know English...
星期一 星期二 星期四 星期三 星期五 星期日 星期六
Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, Wednesday, Friday, Sunday, Saturday.
你好  汤马西诺阁下
Greetings, Don Tommasino.
麦克在教我开车
Michael is teaching me to drive...
我开给你看
watch, I'll show you.
家里的一切都还好吧？
How are things in Palermo?
年轻人不再尊重任何事了
Young people don't respect anything any more...
时代越变越糟
times are changing for the worse.
这地方对你已变得太危险了
This place has become too dangerous for you.
我要你搬到西拉古莎附近的别墅
I want you to move to a villa near Siracusa... right now.
有什么不对了？
What's wrong?
由美国传来的坏消息
Bad news from America.
你哥哥山尼  他们杀了他
Your brother, Santino, they killed him.
我们走了  你答应的
Let's go... you promised.
- 法布利奇欧  - 什么事？
- Fabrizio. - Yes, sir?
备车
Get the car.
你要自己开吗？老板
Are you driving yourself, boss?
是的
Yes.
你太太跟你一起去吗？
Is your wife coming with you?
不  我要你送她回娘家  等一切安全点再说
Take her to her father's house till I know things are safe.
好的  随你吩咐  老板
Anything you say, boss.
卡罗  艾波洛妮亚呢？
Calo, where is Apollonia?
她想给你个惊喜  她要开车
She' going to surprise you. She wants to drive.
她会当个好的美国太太
She'll make a good Amrican wife.
等一下  我去拿行李
Wait, I'll get the baggage.
法布利奇欧
Fabrizio!
你要去哪？
Where are you going?
麦克  在那等  我开过去
Michael. Wait there! I'll drive to you.
不  艾波洛妮亚...
No, Apollonia!
巴西尼阁下
Don Barzini, I want to thank you
谢谢你帮我安排这次会议
for helping me organize this meeting here today.
还有纽约和新泽西其他五大家族的族长
And also the other heads of the five families from New York and New Jersey.
布朗区的卡麦克里安诺
Carmine Cuneo from the Bronx.
以及... 布鲁克林的
From Brooklyn
菲立浦塔塔基利亚
Philip Tattaglia.
由史坦登岛来的
And from Staten Island
维多史特基
we have with us Victor Strachi.
及由加州堪萨斯来的同道
And all the other associates that came as far as from California and Kansas City
以及全国其他各地区所来的朋友
and all the other territories of the country.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
事情怎么会演变成如此？
How did things ever get so far?
我不晓得
I don't know.
是那么的不幸及那么的没必要
It was so unfortunate and so unnecessary.
塔塔基利亚失去了一个儿子
Tattaglia lost a son
我也是
and I lost a son.
我们该停手了
We're quits,
若是塔塔基利亚同意
and if Tattaglia agrees
我愿意让事情恢复以前的局面
then I'm willing to let things go on the way they were before.
我们都很感谢柯里昂阁下召开这次会议
We are all grateful to Don Corleone for calling this meeting.
我们都了解他是个有信用的人
We all know him as a man of his word.
他为人谦虚  总是能讲道理
A modest man. He'll always listen to reason.
是的  巴西尼阁下
Yes, Don Barzini.
他太谦虚了
He's too modest.
所有的法官与政客没有不听他指示的
He had all the judges and politicians in his pocket.
他却拒绝与我们分享
He refused to share them.
我何时拒绝过与大家分享？
When did I ever refuse an accommodation?
在座的全都认识我
All of you know me here.
除了一次以外  我何时拒绝过？
When did I ever refuse, except one time?
你们知道为什么
And why?
因为我相信毒品生意在往后几年会毁了我们
Because I believe this drug business is gonna destroy us in the years to come.
这不像赌 酒和女人
I mean, it's not like gambling or liquor or even women
这些是人们想要的东西只是教会不准我们做而已
which is something that most people want nowadays and is forbidden to them by the pezzonovante of the church.
即使警察过去在赌博等方面愿意协助我们
Even the police departments that have helped us in the past with gambling and other things
但一提到毒品他们会拒绝帮忙
are gonna refuse to help us when it comes to narcotics.
我以前那么想现在想法依然不变
And I believed that then and I believe that now.
时代变了
Times have changed.
不像昔日了
It's not like the old days
我们能做任何我们想做的事
when we could do anything we want.
你拒绝合作实在不够朋友
A refusal is not the act of a friend.
柯里昂阁下握有全纽约法律界以及政客的势力
If Don Corleone had all the judges and politicians in New York
他就必须与大家分享
then he must share them
让大家都能利用他们
or let others use them.
他必须让我们分汲利益大家一起发财
He must let us draw the water from the well.
当然他能因这种服务而向大家收费
Certainly, he can present a bill for such services.
毕竟我们不是共产党
After all, we are not Communists.
我同样的也不相信毒品
I also don't believe in drugs.
多年来我付手下优厚的待遇
For years, I paid my people extra
使他们不去沾毒品
so they wouldn't do that kind of business.
避免有人来找他们并且说我有白粉
Somebody comes to them and says, ''I have powders.
你只要投资三千元到四千元
If you put up a three, four-thousand-dollar investment
就可以赚到五万元
we can make 50,000 distributing.''
他们怎能抗拒得了
So they can't resist.
我想以正派的方法来经营毒品生意
I want to control it as a business to keep it respectable.
我不要它们接近学校
I don't want it near schools.
我不要把它们卖给孩子
I don't want it sold to children.
那是残害幼苗
That's an infamia.
我只想卖给那些黑人或是在有色人种中流通
In my city, we'll keep the traffic in the dark people, the colored.
他们反正是动物  所以让他们去坠落吧
They're animals anyway, so let them lose their souls.
我本希望能合理的讨论一些事
I hoped that we could come here and reason together.
身为一个讲道理的人
As a reasonable man,
我愿意为此事找个和平解决之道
I'm willing to do whatever's necessary to find a peaceful solution to these problems.
那么我们全都达成协议
Then we are agreed.
毒品生意可以做但要有限制
The traffic in drugs will be permitted but controlled.
柯里昂阁下会给我们东部的保护
Don Corleone will give us protection in the east
然后我们和平相处
and there will be the peace.
但我必须有柯里昂阁下的确切保证
But I must have strict assurance from Corleone.
万一他的地位越来越坚固之后
As time goes by and his position becomes stronger
他是否会采取复仇行动
will he attempt any individual vendetta?
听着我们这全是讲理的人
Look, we are all reasonable men here.
我们不需像是律师般给什么确切保证
We don't have to give assurances as if we were lawyers.
你谈到复仇
You talk about vengeance.
复仇会让你的儿子复活吗？
Is vengeance gonna bring your son back to you?
或者我的儿子？
Or my boy to me?
我不会再去计较我儿子的死
I forego the vengeance of my son.
但我有个自私的要求
But I have selfish reasons.
我的小儿子被迫离开这个国家
My youngest son was forced to leave this country
全都因为这索拉索的事
because of this Sollozzo business.
我必须安排让他安全的回来
All right. And I have to make arrangements to bring him back here safely,
洗脱种种无中生有的罪名
cleared of all these false charges.
而我是个迷信的人
But I'm a superstitious man.
若是他不幸发生意外
And if some unlucky accident should
或被警察开枪打死
befall him if he should get shot in the head by a police officer
或在牢里上吊
or if he should hang himself in his jail cell
或是他被闪电击中
of if he's struck by a bolt of lightening-
那我会怪罪于在这房间内的诸位
then I'm going to blame some of the people in this room.
到那时候我就不会再客气了
And that I do not forgive.
但除了那个以外
But that aside
我以我孙子的性命发誓
let me say that I swear on the souls of my grandchildren
我不会是打破我们今天和议的人
that I will not be the one to break the peace we've made here today.
当我见塔塔基利亚的人时
When I meet with the Tattaglia people,
应否坚持那些毒品中间人都没有前科？
should I insist that all these drug middlemen have clean records?
提出来无妨  不要坚持
Mention it. Don't insist.
巴西尼这种人你不说他也明白
Barzini is a man who'll know that without being told.
你是说塔塔基利亚
You mean Tattaglia.
塔塔基利亚是个下三滥？
Tattaglia's a pimp.
他根本没本事干掉山提诺
He never could've outfought Santino.
我在今天以前并不晓得
But I didn't know until this day that it was
一直是巴西尼在主使
Barzini all along.
来吧  南西
Come on, Nancy.
大家紧跟在一起  布莱恩
Keep together, everyone. Brian?
好的...
All right.
你回来多久了？
How long have you been back?
一年了
I've been back a year.
也许还不止
Longer than that, I think.
见到你真好  凯
It's good to see you, Kay.
我现在为我父亲做事
I'm working for my father now, Kay.
他病了  病的很重
He's been sick.Very sick.
但是你不像他  麦克
But you're not like him.
我以为你不会成为令尊那样的人
I thought you weren't going to become a man like your father.
那是你所告诉我的
That's what you told me.
家父与其他有权的人一样
My father's no different than any other powerful man.
就是那种要对其他人负责任的人
Any man who's responsible for other people.
像是参议员或是总统
Like a senator or a president.
你知道你说这些话有多天真
Do you know how naive you sound?
为什么？
Why?
参议员及总统不杀人
Senators and presidents don't have men killed.
是谁天真？凯
Who's being naive, Kay?
家父做事的那一套已过时了
Kay, My father's way of doing things is over.It's finished.
连他都晓得那一点
Even he knows that.
我是说在五年之内
I mean, in five years
柯里昂家族会完全合法化
the Corleone family is going to be completely legitimate.
相信我
Trust me.
我很清楚我未来的走向
That's all I can tell you about my business.
凯
Kay
麦克  你为何到这来？
Why did you come here?
为什么？
Why?
你究竟想要我怎么样？
What do you want with me
这么多年来你不打电话也不写信
after all this time without even calling or writing?
我来这是因为我需要你  我关心你
I came here because I need you. Because I care for you.
别再说了  麦克
- Please stop it, Michael.
因为...
- Because...
我要你嫁给我
I want you to marry me.
太迟了
- It's too late. - Please.
凯
Kay
我会做任何事以弥补过去所发生的事
I'll do anything you ask to make up for what's happened to us.
因为那很重要  凯
Because that's important.
重要的是因为
Because what's important is that
我们拥有彼此
we have each other.
而且我们要共度一生
That we have a life together.
我们会有孩子
That we have children-
我们的孩子
our children.
凯
Kay
我需要你
I need you
而且我爱你
and I love you.
巴西尼的人抢我们的地盘
Barzini's people chisel my territory
而我们却无能为力
and we do nothing about it.
再过不久布鲁克林连我落脚的地方都没有了
Soon, there won't be one place in Brooklyn I can hang my hat.
有耐性点
Just be patient.
我不是求你帮忙  只是不想受制肘
I'm not askin' you for help. Just take off the handcuffs.
再忍耐点
Be patient.
我们必须保护自己
We gotta protect ourselves.
给我个机会再培养一些新人
Give me a chance to recruit some new men.
不
No.
- 我不要给巴西尼藉口来开战  - 麦克  你错了
- I don't wanna give Barzini an excuse to start fighting.- Mike, you're wrong.
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone,
你曾说过要让我与泰西欧自立门户
you once said the day would come when Tessio and me could form our own family.
今天以前我想都不敢想
Till today, I would never think of it.
但现在我要求你的批准
I must ask your permission.
现在由麦克当家  如果他答应我就祝福你
Well, Michael is now head of the family and if he gives his permission, then you have my blessing.
等我们搬到内华达州后
After we make the move to Nevada
你就可由柯里昂家族分出自立门户
you can break off from the Corleone family and go on your own.
但得在我们搬到内华达州之后
After we make the move to Nevada.
那得花多少时间？
How long will that be?
六个月
Six months.
原谅我  教父
Forgive me, Godfather,
但当你走了后
but with you gone
我与彼得迟早会成为巴西尼的靶
me and Pete'll come under Barzini's thumb sooner or later.
我恨那该死的巴西尼
And I hate that goddamn Barzini.
六个月之后我们已经搞不出什么玩意了
In six months' time, there won't be nothing left to build on.
你对我的判断有信心吗？
You have faith in my judgment?
是的
Yes.
你仍对我忠心吗？
Do I have your loyalty?
是的  忠心不二  教父
Yes, Always, Godfather.
那么就当麦克的朋友吧
Then be a friend to Michael
照他所说的去做
and do as he says.
现在有些事仍在磋商
There are things being negotiated now
你们的问题和困难全都可以得到解决
that are gonna solve all your problems and answer all your questions.
目前我只能这么说
That's all I can tell you now.
卡洛  你在内华达长大的
Carlo, you grew up in Nevada.
当我们搬的时候  你会是我的左右手
When we make our move there, you're gonna be my right-hand man.
汤姆哈金不再做军师了
Tom Hagen's no longer consigliere.
他将会担任我们在拉斯维加斯的律师
He's gonna be our lawyer in Vegas.
我对汤姆没有不满  但我不要他再当军师
That's no reflection on Tom, but that's the way I want it.
况且有我父亲在  他可以做我最佳的军师
Besides, if I ever need help who's a better consigliere than my father?
就是这样了
That's it.
- 谢谢  爸爸  - 我为你高兴  卡洛
- Thank you, Papa. - I'm happy for you, Carlo.
麦克  我为何出局了？
Mike... Why am I out?
你不适合当乱局中的军师
You're not a wartime consigliere, Tom.
我们一搬到内华达后  事情会变得更棘手
Things may get rough with the move we're trying.
汤姆
Tom
我向麦克建议过
I advised Michael.
我从未认为你不适合当军师
I never thought you were a bad consigliere.
我认为山提诺不适合当家
I thought Santino was a bad Don
愿他安息
rest in peace.
我信任麦克和你一样
Michael has all my confidence, as you do.
但是...
But...
不让你参与往后的行动是有理由的
there are reasons why you must have no part of what is going to happen.
我多少能帮得上忙
Maybe I could help.
用不着了  汤姆
- You're out, Tom.
我实在无法不去注意你的脸
I can't get over the way your face looks.
它的确看起来很棒
It really looks good.
这位医生的工夫确实不错
This doctor did some job.
是凯说服你去的吗？
Who talked you into it, Kay?
慢着  把它们留下这
Hey, hey, wait. Leave them out here.
我们待会再处理它们
We'll deal with them later.
他累了  他想梳洗一下
He's tired. He wants to clean up.
好了  让我来开门  好吗？
Now, let me open the door.
麦克  欢迎光临拉斯维加斯
Hello, Mike. Welcome to Las Vegas.
你认为如何？
All for you, kid.
全是他的主意  对吧？
It was all his idea, right?
你的哥哥弗雷多
Well, your brother, Freddy-
是你弄来的女孩子  不是吗？
It was Girls?
我马上回来  你先招呼一下
I'll be right back. You keep them occupied.
- 你要什么全都有  - 那些女孩子是谁？
- That a boy. Anything you want, kid.- Who are the girls?
这得要你自己去弄清楚了
That's for you to find out.
把她们弄走  弗雷多
- Get rid of them, Fredo.
麦克
Hey, Mike-
弗雷多  我是来这公干
Fredo, I'm here on business.
我明天就走  现在把她们弄走
I leave tomorrow. Now, get rid of them.
我累了  把乐队也弄走
I'm tired. Get rid of the band too.
走吧  走就对了
Hey, just take off. Come on. Let's go.
快点  安琪拉  快走
Hey, that's it. Angelo, that's it.
走吧  闪了
Let's go. Hey, come on!
走吧  亲爱的  走了
Scram! Come on, honey. Let's go.
我不知道  强尼
I don't know,Johnny.
我不知道他是怎么回事对不起
I don't know what the hell's the matter with him.
没关系  弗雷多
It's all right, Freddy.
走吧  亲爱的我不知道  他大概累了
I don't know. He's tired, he's hot.
莫格林呢？
What happened to Moe Greene?
他说他有别的事
He said he had some business.
他说派对开始时  给他个电话
He said give him a call when the party started.
那就打电话给他
Well, give him a call.
强尼  你好吗？
- Johnny, how are you?
麦克  再看到你真高兴
Hello. Nice to see you again.
我们全都以你为傲
We're all proud of you.
谢谢  麦克
Thanks, Mike.
坐  强尼  我要跟你谈谈
Sit down,Johnny. I want to talk to you.
教父也以你为傲  强尼
The Don's proud of you too, Johnny.
我的一切都归功于他
I owe it all to him.
他知道你会感恩
Well, he knows how grateful you are.
所以他想请你帮个忙
That's why he'd like to ask a favor of you.
麦克  我能做些什么？
Mike, what can I do?
柯里昂家族想放弃橄榄油的生意
The Corleone family is thinking of giving up all its interests in the olive oil business,
而在这里安顿下来
settling out here.
莫格林会把他旅馆及赌场的股份卖给我们
Now, Moe Greene will sell us his share of the casino and hotel
使得家族能拥有全部的生意
so it can be completely owned by the family.
汤姆
Tom.
麦克  这点你确定吗？
Mike, are you sure about that?
莫格林很爱这门生意
Moe loves the business.
从未对我提过要卖掉它的事
He never said nothing about selling.
我会提个他无法拒绝的条件
I'll make him an offer he can't refuse.
知道吗？强尼...
See,Johnny
我们认为表演一定可以吸引赌客到赌场来
we figure that entertainment will be a big factor in drawing gamblers to the casino.
我们希望你签个合约一年来此登台五次
We hope you'll sign a contract to appear five times a year.
也许...
Perhaps...
顺便找些你电影圈中的朋友
convince some of your friends in the movies to do the same.
我指望你了
We're counting on you.
当然  麦克
Sure, Mike.
为了教父我什么都肯做  你晓得的
I'll do anything for my godfather. You know that.
很好
Good.
麦克  各位好  大家都在这
Hey, Mike! Hello, fellows. Everybody's here.
弗雷多  汤姆...
Freddy, Tom.
- 见到你真好  麦克  - 你好吗？莫
Good to see you, Mike. How are you, Moe?
你点的都到齐了吗？
You got everything you want?
大厨会为你煮最好吃的菜还有最棒的舞群
The chef cooked for you special, the dancers will kick your tongue out and your credit is good.
给房间里的每个人都弄点筹码来
Draw chips for everybody in the room
好让他们到场子里去玩玩
so they can play on the house.
我的信用好的够买下你的股份吗？
My credit good enough to buy you out?
买我的股份？
Buy me out?
赌场  这家旅馆
The casino. The hotel.
柯里昂家族想买下你全部的生意
The Corleone family wants to buy you out.
柯里昂家族想买下我全部的生意？
The Corleone family wants to buy me out?
不  我买下你们的你不能买下我的
No, I buy you out. You don't buy me out.
你的赌场在赔钱
Your casino loses money.
也许我们能经营的好一点
Maybe we can do better.
你认为我在走下坡了？麦克
You think I'm skimming off the top, Mike?
你运气不好
You're unlucky.
你他妈的别让我笑了
You goddamn guineas really make me laugh.
在你们有难时
I do you a favor and
我帮你们的忙给弗雷多一份差事
take Freddy in when you're having a bad time.
现在你想把我弄出去
- Then you try to push me out!
慢着
Wait a minute.
你让弗雷多来这
You took Freddy in
是因为柯里昂家族支援你的赌场
because the Corleone family bankrolled your casino
因为海岸的莫伦纳家族
because the Molinari family on the coast
保证他的安全
guaranteed his safety.
现在我们在谈生意别岔开话题
Now, we're talkin' business. Let's talk business.
好  我们来谈生意  麦克
Let's talk business, Mike.
首先  你们都完蛋了
First of all, you're all done.
柯里昂家族已经衰退了
The Corleone family don't have that kind of muscle anymore.
教父生病了  对吧？
The Godfather's sick.
你们被巴西尼及其他家族赶出了纽约
You're getting chased out of New York by Barzini and the other families.
你以为这里是什么？
What do you think is going on it?
你以为能到我的地盘上来接管？
You think you can come to my hotel and take over?
我和巴西尼谈过了
I talked to Barzini.
我有办法和他打交道
I can make a deal with him
也不至于失去旅馆
and still keep my hotel.
所以你当众支使我哥哥？
Is that why you slapped my brother around in public?
不  麦克  那不算什么
That was nothing, Mike.
莫也不是那个意思
Moe didn't mean nothing by that.
当然他偶尔说话很大声  但是
Sure he flies off the handle once in a while but
莫和我是好朋友  对吧？莫
but Moe and me, we're good friends, right?
我是在做事业
I got a business to run.
当然要催紧点  事情才会顺利
I gotta kick asses sometimes to make it run right.
我是偶尔和弗雷多意见不合
We had a little argument,
只不过是为了''训练''他一下
so I had to straighten him out.
你''训练''我哥哥？
You straightened my brother out?
他跟酒廊的女侍鬼混
He was banging cocktail waitresses two at a time!
客人喝酒没人送
Players couldn't get a drink.
你是怎么回事？
What's wrong with you?
我明天回纽约
I leave for New York tomorrow.
你考虑一个价钱吧
Think about a price.
你知道我是谁吗？我是莫格林
Son of a bitch. Do you know who I am? I'm Moe Greene.
我发迹时你还在玩泥巴
I made my bones when you were going out with cheerleaders.
等一等  莫  我有个主意
Wait a minute. I got an idea.
汤姆  汤姆  你是军师
Tom, you're the consigliere.
你可以和教父谈  解释给他听
- You can talk to the Don. You can explain
慢着  教父已经半退休了
Just a minute. Don is semi-retired and
家族现在由麦克管事
Mike is in charge of the business now.
你有话就向麦克说吧
If you have anything to say, say it to Michael.
麦克  你不能到拉斯维加斯来
Mike, You don't come to Las Vegas
和莫格林那种人那样说话
and talk to Moe Greene like that!
弗雷多
Freddy.
你是我哥  我爱你
You're my older brother, and I love you.
但不准你再联合外人起来反对自己家族
But don't ever take sides with anyone against the family again
我必须先去看我父亲和他的手下
I have to see my father and his people.
你们先吃饭吧
Have dinner without me.
麦克
Michael
这个周末我们可以出外游玩
This weekend we'll go out.
到城里看电影吃饭  我保证
We'll go to the city. We'll see a show and have dinner. I promise.
麦克
Michael
麦克  你姐姐有事想问你
Your sister wants to ask you something.
- 她可以问我  - 她怕你
- Let her ask. - She's afraid to.
康妮和卡洛要你当他们孩子的教父
Connie and Carlo want you to be godfather to their little boy.
- 到时再说吧  - 你会吗？
- We'll see. - Will you?
让我考虑一下到时再说  来吧
Let me think about it. Come on.
巴西尼想要先对付你
So Barzini will move against you first.
他会找个你信任的人来安排见面
He'll set up a meeting with someone that you absolutely trust
并保证你的安全
guaranteeing your safety.
但你一出席会议  他就杀了你
And at that meeting, you'll be assassinated.
我现在比以前爱喝酒了
I like to drink wine more than I used to.
而且越爱喝就喝的越多
Anyway, I'm drinking more.
对你有好处的  爸爸
It's good for you, Pop.
我不知道
I don't know.
你太太和小孩过的还快乐吧？
Your wife and children, are you happy with them?
非常快乐
Very happy.
很好
That's good.
希望你不介意我一直在谈巴西尼
I hope you don't mind the way I I keep going over this Barzini business.
不  一点也不
No, not at all.
这是我的老习惯
It's an old habit.
我花了一辈子就学会了''小心''
I spent my life tryin' not to be careless.
女人和小孩能够粗心大意  但男人不行
Women and children can be careless, but not men.
- 你儿子还好吗？  - 很好
- How's your boy? - He's good.
你知道他越来越像你了
You know, he looks more like you every day.
他比我聪明
He's smarter than I am.
才三岁就懂得看漫画了
Three years old, he can read the funny papers.
看漫画
He reads the funny papers.
我要你安排一个电话公司的人
I want you to arrange to have a telephone man
查每一个进出这里的电话
check all the calls that go in and out of here.
- 我已经做了  爸  - 任何一个人都有可能
- I did it already. - Could be anyone.
- 爸  我已经处理那件事了  - 没错  我忘了
- I took care of that. - That's right. I forgot.
怎么回事？
What's the matter?
是什么困扰着你？
What's bothering you?
我应付得了  我说能  我就能
I'll handle it. I told you I can handle it, I'll handle it.
我知道山提诺势必会染指家族事业
I knew that Santino was gonna have to go through all this
还有弗雷多
and Fredo-
弗雷多他...
Fredo was-
但我从来没...
But I never...
我从来没想到要你参与
I never wanted this for you.
我干了一辈子  没什么遗憾的
I worked my whole life- I don't apologize-
我照顾了我的家人
to take care of my family
但是我绝不当傻瓜
and I refused to be a fool
让那些大人物在幕后操纵我
dancing on a string held by all those big shots.
我不必道歉  那是我的命运但是我想过...
I don't apologize. That's my life. But I thought that-
有一天你能当那些操纵的人
that when it was your time you would be the one to hold the strings.
柯里昂参议员
Senator Corleone.
柯里昂州长之类的
Governor Corleone. Something.
再建立一个王国
Another pezzonovante.
这个... 时间不多了  麦克时间不多了
Just wasn't enough time, Michael. Wasn't enough time.
我们会做到的  爸
We'll get there, Pop.
我们会做到的
We'll get there.
你听好...
Listen,
谁请你去和巴西尼开会
whoever comes to you with this Barzini meeting
他就是叛徒
he's the traitor.
千万别忘了
Don't forget that.
能让我拿吗？
我能自己浇水
Can I water these
我可以浇水吗？
- Can I water these?
可以  浇吧
- Yeah. That's fine.
这里  来这里
Over here. Over here.
小心点  别溅到了  小心
Be careful. You're spilling it. You're spilling it.
安东尼  过来  来吧...
Anthony, come here. Come here.
来这里
Come here.
对了  放在这
That's right. We'll put it right there.
来  有东西给你看
I'll show you something. Come here.
来这
Come here.
你站好
Now, you stand there.
把柳丁给我
Give me an orange!
别怕
这是新把戏
That's a new trick.
你去里面  去里面
You run in there. Run in there.
你在哪？
- Where are you? - Who?
倒下去
Ouch!
麦克  能借一步说话吗？
Mike, can I have a minute?
巴西尼想要安排一次会议
Barzini wants to arrange a meeting.
他说任何的问题都可以谈出一个解决之道
He says we can straighten any of our problems out.
- 你和他谈过了？  - 是的
- You talked to him? - Yeah.
我能安排安全事宜
I can arrange security
在我的地盘上  好吗？
on my territory. All right?
- 好的  - 好
- All right. - All right.
你知道他们预备怎么对付你吗？
Do you know how they're gonna come at you?
他们安排在布鲁克林开会
They're arranging a meeting in Brooklyn.
泰西欧的地盘上
Tessio's ground
说在那我会安全的
where I'll be safe.
我一直以为是克里曼沙  没想到是泰西欧
I always thought it would've been Clemenza, not Tessio.
这一招漂亮  泰西欧一向聪明
It's the smart move. Tessio was always smarter.
但我会静观其变
But I'm gonna wait.
等洗礼过了再说
After the baptism.
我决定当康妮小孩的教父了
I've decided to be godfather to Connie's baby.
然后我再去见巴西尼
And then I'll meet with Don Barzini
还有塔塔基利亚
and Tattaglia
所有五大家族的族长
all the heads of the five families.
（意大利文祷词）
阿门
Amen!
（意大利文祷词）
麦克  你相信上帝吗？
Michael, do you believe in God,
全能的天父  万物的创造者
the Father Almighty creator of Heaven and Earth?
我相信
I do.
你相信耶稣基督他的独子  我们的主吗？
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, his only Son, our Lord?
我相信
I do.
你相信圣灵  神圣的教堂吗？
Do you believe in the holy Ghost, the holy Catholic Church?
我相信
I do.
（意大利文祷词）
麦克柯里昂
Michael Francis Rizzi,
你弃绝撒旦吗？
do you renounce Satan?
我弃绝
I do renounce him.
包括他所有的作为吗？
And all his works?
我弃绝
I do renounce them.
包括他所有的虚伪？
- And all his pomps?
我弃绝
I do renounce them.
麦克柯里昂
Michael Rizzi,
你愿意当他的教父吗？
will you be baptized?
我愿意
I will.
（意大利文祷词）
麦克柯里昂
Michael Rizzi
愿主与你同在  阿门
Go in peace, and may the Lord be with you. Amen.
凯
Kay.
这是你的教父
This is your godfather.
- 卡洛  - 什么事
- Carlo. - What?
我现在不能去拉斯维加斯
Can't go to Vegas.
临时有要事  让他们先走吧
Something's come up.
- 麦克  这是我们第一次度假  - 康妮  别吵
- It's our first vacation together. - Connie, please.
- 你要我怎么做  - 回家去等我电话  有要事
- What do you wanna do? - Go back to the house. Wait for my call. It's important.
好的
Ok.
我只需一两天
I'll only be a couple of days.
旅途愉快  妈
Have a nice trip, Mama.
我们要去布鲁克林了
We're on our way to Brooklyn.
我希望麦克今晚能谈个好交易
I hope Mike can get us a good deal tonight.
他一定会的
I'm sure he will.
沙尔  汤姆
Sal, Tom,
老板说他自己坐车来
the boss says he'll come in a separate car.
叫你们先走
He says for you two to go on ahead.
他不能那么做
He can't do that.
- 弄乱了我所有的安排  - 他是这么说的
It screws up all my arrangements. That's what he said.
我也不能去  沙尔
I can't go either, Sal.
告诉麦克这纯粹是生意
Tell Mike it was only business.
我一直都喜欢他
I always liked him.
他会了解的  沙尔
He understands that.
抱歉了  沙尔
Excuse me, Sal.
汤姆  能替我求个情吗？
Can you get me off the hook?
- 看在老交情的份上  - 我做不到  沙尔
- For old times' sake. - Can't do it, Sally.
你得为山尼的事偿命  卡洛
You have to answer for Santino, Carlo.
- 你误会了  麦克  - 你为巴西尼的人设计害山尼
You got it all wrong. You fingered Sonny for the Barzini people.
你和我姐姐演的那场闹剧
That little farce you played with my sister.
以为骗得过柯里昂家的人吗？
Did you think that could fool a Corleone?
麦克  我是清白的
I'm innocent.
我以我的孩子来发誓
I swear on the kids.
- 求你  麦克  别这样对我  - 坐下
- Please, don't do this to me. - Sit down.
麦克  别这样对我  求你
Don't do this to me, please.
巴西尼死了
Barzini's dead.
菲立浦塔塔基利亚也死了
So is Phillip Tattaglia
还有莫格林  史特基克里安诺
Moe Greene Strachi Cuneo.
今天我一次清理整个家族的事
Today I settle all family business,
所以别跟我说你是无辜的  卡洛
so don't tell me you're innocent.
承认你所做过的
Admit what you did.
给他一杯酒
Get him a drink.
说吧
Come on.
别怕  卡洛
Don't be afraid, Carlo.
你以为我忍心让我姐姐当寡妇？
You think I'd make my sister a widow?
我又是你儿子的教父  卡洛
I'm godfather to your son, Carlo.
喝吧
Go ahead, drink.
卡洛  从此你退出家族的生意  这是给你的惩罚
No, you're out of the family business. That's your punishment.
你玩完了  我送你上飞机去拉斯维加斯
You're finished. I'm putting you on a plane to Vegas.
汤姆
Tom
我要你留在那边  明白吗？
I want you to stay there. Understand?
只是别告诉我你是无辜的
Only don't tell me you're innocent
因为那等于把我当傻瓜
because it insults my intelligence.
会让我非常生气
It makes me very angry.
现在  是谁和你接头的？
Now, who approached you?
塔塔基利亚还是巴西尼？
Tattaglia or Barzini?
是巴西尼
It was Barzini.
好
Good.
外面有辆车等着送你去机场
There's a car waiting for you outside to take you to the airport.
我通知你太太  说你坐那班飞机
I'll call your wife, tell her what flight you're on.
- 麦克  我...   - 快走  别让我看到你
- Please, can I- - Get out of my sight.
卡洛
Hello, Carlo.
你想告诉我什么？
Will you stop crying? What are you trying to tell me?
- 我想告诉你...   - 妈妈  拜托...
- I'm telling you you're wrong. - Mama, please!
麦克...
Michael
- 怎么了？  - 他在哪儿？麦克
Where is he?
麦克  你这混蛋你杀了我丈夫
Michael, you lousy bastard! You killed my husband!
你看爸一死  就没人能管你了
You waited until Papa died so nobody could stop you
所以你就把他杀了
and then you killed him!
你一直把山尼的死怪在他身上
You blamed him for Sonny.
你一直如此  大家都如此
You always did. Everybody did.
但你有没有想过我？
But you never thought about me!
从来不在乎我
You never gave a damn about me!
我以后要怎么办？
Now what am I gonna do?
康妮...
Connie
你以为他为何要卡洛在他身边
Why do you think he kept Carlo at the mall?
他早就算计好要杀他
All the time he knew he was gonna kill him.
你还是我孩子的教父
And you stood godfather to our baby.
你这个冷酷的混蛋
You lousy, coldhearted bastard.
你知道除了卡洛他还杀过多少人吗？
Want to know how many men he had killed with Carlo?
看看报纸吧...
Read the papers! Read the papers!
是你丈夫...
That's your husband! That's your husband!
不要...
No!
带她上楼
Take her upstairs.
找医生来
- Get her a doctor.
她神经错乱了
She's hysterical.
歇斯底里
Hysterical.
麦克  是真的吗？
Michael, Is it true?
- 我跟你说过别管公事  凯  - 是真的吗？
- Don't ask me about my business, Kay.- Is it true?
别过问我的公事
Don't ask me about my business.
- 不  - 够了
- No! - Enough!
好吧
All right.
只此一次
This one time.
这次我让你问吧
This one time, I'll let you ask me about my affairs.
是真的吗？
Is it true?
不是
No.
我想我们两个都需要喝一杯
I guess we both need a drink, huh?
我去倒
Come on.
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone.